recording in progress.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen. I
would like to call the April 27th
meeting of the governing body to order
and ask the clerk to take the role.
>> Mr. Esabel,
>> here.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> Mr. Moody,
>> here.
>> Dr. Mr. Renie,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> present.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> here.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> present.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> present.
>> One member is absent. We do have a
quorum.
>> Would you all join me, please, in the
pledge of allegiance?
Consent agenda. All agenda items listed
with the designation of CA are
considered to be routine items by the
governing body and will be enacted by
one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
and support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
All right. Are there any items a member
of the governing body would like to
remove from the consent agenda?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Lebornne,
>> number 15.
>> That's our six penny sales tax.
>> Concur.
>> Okay. 15 has been removed,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes.
>> Number 29A.
That's the purchase of the land for the
greenway.
>> Concur.
>> Any other items?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Lebornne.
>> And number 29D,
that's an FTA grant for our transit
facility.
>> Yep.
>> Concur.
Anybody else on the governing body? All
right. Hearing none, I would entertain a
motion.
>> Move to approve. Second.
>> All right. We have a motion to approve
the consent agenda with items 15, 29A,
and 29D removed. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed. The consent agenda is
approved.
>> Number six, ordinance, third reading,
amending section 13.20.050. 050 general
prohibitions in section 13.20.070
local limits of chapter 13.20 wastewater
treatment and disposal of the code of
the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to revise
local discharge limits and related
provisions in compliance with MPDES and
WPDEES permit requirements.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Is anybody interested in talking about
our wastewater treatment disposal codes?
Looks like you're off the hook, Matt.
Hearing none, I would entertain a
motion. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading. And I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Aldridge. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated April 7th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved to substitute. Uh
seconded by Dr. Aldridge.
Um, and I understand it all it does is
just changes some of the the percentages
and corrects the percentages so um we
can uh have the right numbers in there.
Anybody in the audience want to talk
about that substitute?
>> How about from the governing body?
Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> Those opposed. All right. The amendment
or substitute is adopted. We're back on
the main motion.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. ments.
>> I move to postpone until the May 11th,
2026 meeting of the governing body.
>> Second.
>> Second by Dr. Aldridge. And that
postponement is so that we can catch up
with the 30-day comment period from the
EPA. Um, sometimes we'll just do these
and hold them till it's done, but we
decided to wait on this one. Anybody in
the audience want to speak to the
postponement
on the governing body?
Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed? All right. This ordinance
is postponed until May 11th.
>> Number seven, ordinance, third reading,
amending section 2.76.040,
designation of downtown Development
District of chapter 2.76, Downtown
Development Authority of Title 2,
Administration and Personnel of the
Municipal Code of the City of Cheyenne,
Wyoming to expand the downtown
development district.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience here today that would like to
speak to the expansion of our DDA
district?
Hearing
none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on third and final reading. And I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Comments from
members of the governing body on the
expansion.
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk, would you
take the vote?
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> I.
>> Mr. Esbel.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Hi.
>> There you go.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. White.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> The ordinance is approved on third and
final reading.
>> Number eight, ordinance, third reading,
appropriating money for the Reed Avenue
corridor project.
>> All right. All right. Is there anybody
in the audience would like to speak
about the city council's intention to
appropriate $5 million for the Reed
Avenue corridor project if and when the
railroad gives us permission.
Jim, welcome. Mr. Mayor, thank you. Good
evening, Mr. Mayor, council members. For
the record, my name is Jim Walter. I
serve as the president and CEO of Visit
Cheyenne, our community's destination
marketing organization. and I also
currently chair the greenway advisory
committee and I'm a W three resident.
I'm here tonight in support of moving
the Reed Avenue corridor project
forward. From my perspective, there's
three reasons to consider a yes vote.
First, this is the kind of project we
should find a way to fund. It's
destination defining. I commend council
for finding a path forward without
placing an additional burden on
taxpayers. If there's a path to an
advanced and important piece of city
infrastructure forward without going
back to residents for more, that's worth
serious consideration.
Secondly, this project aligns with the
Cheyenne tourism master plan. On page
12, the plan specifically calls out the
Reed Avenue corridor as part of
developing the west edge of downtown.
That same section also highlights
improving downtown infrastructure and
appearance as a priority because those
investments shape how residents and
visitors experience Cheyenne.
Third, a stronger and more vibrant
downtown attracts continued private
investment. We've seen a lot of private
investment on the West Edge already.
Public infrastructure is often what
gives the private sector the confidence
to move forward. When we improve access,
appearance, and connectivity, we create
conditions for more retail, lodging,
dining, housing, and other business
development. Here at Visit Cheyenne, we
believe downtown matters because it's
one of the clearest expressions of our
community to visitors and residents
alike. Reed Avenue is not just a
corridor project. It's a signal about
where Cheyenne is heading. Thank you for
your consideration.
>> Well said, Jim. Thank you. Anybody else?
>> Mr. Escoel,
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve on third
and final reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Been seconded by Mr. White. Comments
from members of the governing body on
the ordinance. Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Mayor, I think that uh what uh the
visit Cheyenne just said pretty much
covered it, but I want to emphasize this
is following through on a long planned
and a project that was on the ballot
some years ago. We're now going to fund
it. And I think that's very important
and hopefully it'll be part of the
discussion of the sixth penny because
this is uh the followup to that project.
So um I think we're ready to uh move on
it and I expect the railroad to finally
approve and we can actually support the
businesses that have invested. Thank
you.
>> Dr. Aldridge. Mayor Collins through you.
I know there's been a lot of
conversation about whether we should
take $5 million from our general reserve
to fund this uh Reed Avenue corridor
project. I'm going to be a yes vote
tonight. And the reason for that is
because this is a a project that was
started um prior to my term on uh
council um five years ago. And there was
a commitment, I believe, that the voters
of Cheyenne voted to support this
project on that six penny ballot. and
the money I think just didn't go far
enough quite honestly. Um there were
some missteps, definitely some things
that we could have done better probably
as a city government. Um but I think
that over time the expense has also
increased dramatically um with increased
pricing and um materials and things. I
think that there's also been a lot of
footwork that's been done and a lot of
foundational work that's been laid with
the um BNSF railroad um in order to get
this far. And the reason I'll be voting
to support this tonight is because this
is contingent upon an an approved plan
by the BNSF railroad. If they don't
approve the plan and give the final
okay, this money will not be spent from
the general reserves. So, for that
reason, I will be a yes vote tonight.
But I wanted to make sure that people
understood that this is a project that
was started early on and that we have a
commitment I believe to finish a project
that voters voted on and expected us to
continue uh through completion.
>> Anyone else in the governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor, Dr. Renie.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Mr. Mayor, I um I agree with my
colleagues and I agree with what Mr.
Walter said. Um, we did approach the
voters with a vision for Reed Avenue
corridor and it was approved on the Six
Benny in 2017. And when we did it, we
realized, we knew at the time, but it
would give us a start. It would give us
a plan. It would not get us to
completion. And we also knew at some
point we would have to come back and
spend more money on it. How if we were
going to complete it. However, um we
have a couple big asks coming up to the
to the voters in the next few months. Um
I the reason I don't like this in
ordinance form, it means it's law. It
means it's if it's passed, it mean
I think we lost you. Can you hear us?
Dr. Annie.
>> All right, we'll move on. Anybody else
in the governing body?
>> All right, hearing none. Madam clerk,
would you take the vote?
>> Mayor Collins?
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Emmens?
>> I.
>> Mr. Esabel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yes.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> yes.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> All right. This ordinance is approved on
third and final reading with Mr. Moody
voting no. And we lost Dr. Rainey.
>> Number nine, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne. change changing the
zoning classification for land located
south of I80 east of Southwest Drive
from County LI Light Industrial, AG
Agricultural, and AR Agricultural
Residential to LI Light Industrial.
>> All right. Is there anybody here in the
audience today that would like to speak
to the zone change before us?
>> I'm hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public service committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Wolf.
>> Do we have any comments from members of
the governing body on the zone change on
second reading?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed. This ordinance is
approved on second reading.
>> Number 10, ordinance, second reading,
pursuant to section 2.2.2, to planned
development regulating plan or
development master plan and section
5.6.2 PUD planned unit development
district of the U unified development
code amending ordinance number 4524 by
modifying certain standards of the
adopted district planning unit
development PUD for sweetg grass located
southeast of the intersection of College
Drive and Avenue C.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Is anybody here today to speak to the
change to this plan unit development?
>> Mr. Palma, welcome.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor, members of
council. Casey Palma, Palmer land
planning agent for the owner. Um, so I
what you have before you tonight is a
PUD amendment. Um as written in the PUD
uh any change to any major change to the
regulations requires uh governing body
approval as the governing body was the
original body of the plan unit
development zoning. Uh this amendment
would allow for um sort of a sharing of
the originally anticipated park area.
So, uh, the total park requirement is
about 67 acres and the city would like
to develop about 45 of that as a private
park. Um, and so that remainder of the
originally proposed parcel uh would then
be able to with this amendment be
developed for privately for private
purposes uh potentially with indoor
fieldhouse, playgrounds, trails, that
kind of thing. Um this PUD this actually
increases the total amount of of open
space and park required because uh this
would not erase the other 22 that that
was required with the original proposal.
So there would be uh sort of a reserved
area for future park uh with this
amendment.
And so we we've as everybody knows you
know wanted to develop that park for a
long time. Um and so this this would be
a way for the the city and and
Sweetgrass to to start to move forward
on getting that park development to
happen. Um the commercial area has been
a little slow in developing. There's a
lot of residents out there and we'd like
to go ahead and get get started on on
developing that park for them uh
handinhand with the city. I have had
conversations with the parks department
about how to move that forward over the
next year. Um and so this this amendment
allows that to happen. Uh the only other
thing in here um that was kind of a
bookkeeping type of item is this would
allow for zone changes to happen within
the PUD. So PUD is laid out just like
the city of Cheyenne with different zone
districts, low density, high density,
commercial, that type of thing. Uh this
amendment also includes a provision that
would allow for a land owner within the
PUB to petition the committee to change
the zone of their ownership. you know
whether it was originally supposed to be
a a commercial and then it wants to go
to residential or high density to low
density residential or vice versa. Uh
this would be the just basically enable
the regular zoning change process within
the city for any land within the PUD to
change to any other zoning within the
PUD.
Be happy to address any questions you
might have.
>> Does anybody have any questions for the
applicant? Mr. Moody.
>> Yep.
>> Thank you, M. Mayor for you. Uh thank
you, sir. Um, so I'm assuming that the
HOA of SweetGrass is okay with this.
They had a meeting. They contact all
their residents and they're perfectly
okay with this.
>> Uh, I can't speak to whether the HOA had
a meeting yet on this item. Uh, we did
notify every landowner within the PUD
and every landowner within 300 ft. I've
fielded about a dozen calls probably.
Um, nobody had any opposition that I
heard and I I don't believe staff has
had any opposition once once the
amendment was explained as to what was
going on here.
>> All right. Thank you. I have no further
questions.
>> Anybody else in the governing body for
the staff? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Eric Collins for you. Um, thank you, Mr.
Palma, for the email that you sent. Um,
I have two concerns. One is the ability
for the land owner to be able to do a
zone change. Um,
do you anticipate from the way that I
read um the proposed um ordinance
change, it would um basically preempt,
if you will, um any conversation with
the um folks that would be impacted by
those zone changes um because it allows
the owner to do that um without the
normal process. Is that um how you're
perceiving that as well? Is that the
owner would then be able to do those
much more quickly and efficiently?
>> So, Mr. Palm, is this an administrative
thing the owner gets to do?
>> Um, no, Mr. Mayor, through you. Uh, I
apologize. I may have abbreviated it a
little bit in in the effort of time. Uh,
so within the PD is a plan unit
development. And so what this would do
is allow any land owner there there is a
committee a review committee uh to make
sure that the development is is
proceeding as planned. Uh so this would
allow those land owners to petition the
committee uh to to make a zone change
and then it would go through the regular
city zone change process just like you
hear any other zone change um as long as
the committee was in favor. And
additionally it's it's more restrictive
than the city zone change process
because uh you can only change up to 25%
of a parcel. So, say you owned a big,
you know, multif family parcel and you
wanted to reszone part of it. Uh, if
that was more than 25%, then it would it
would turn into a major amendment.
>> Thank you. And one additional question,
Mayor.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, for you, my last
question is simply about the uh proposed
division of the park property. Um, I
know in your email that you had said you
had talked with um our uh community
wreck and events director and that uh
really our limitation would be about 45
um acres. Is that right? Um that we
could suitably maintain and manage as as
a city entity. Um and that there was um
you just mentioned an indoor practice
facility that was being considered for
some of the other acreage. Um to bring
that up to that uh total of 60 plus
acres with that. My concern is that that
indoor practice facility would not
necessarily be a public facility. Um, is
that correct in my understanding?
>> Um, that is correct. I believe they've
had some conversations. I'm I'm not uh
they're not my client. I haven't had
been party to all of those
conversations, but I know they have had
some conversations with the city uh
parks department and and other
departments about, you know, making some
arrangements similar to maybe how the
beast used to be. Um I I can't speak to
sort of their whole uh plan. I think we
would be excited to see something there.
I've talked to them about um providing
some sort of you know either either
discounted rates or certain hours
available to residents of Sweetgrass um
but it would not be a public facility
which is part of why you know we we've
said we don't want to reduce the total
requirement. So even if this park this
does come in there um I think our
preference would be to then provide
future open space elsewhere in the PUD
um that would be potentially a public
park. So there's no intent that the PD
uh on the whole is about 40% planned
open space. Um and so we intend to
continue with that. Um this is not an
attempt to reduce any required open
space just to set aside a specific
acreage that would be developable and
maintainable by the city.
>> Thank you.
>> Dr. Al, I can maybe add a little bit to
that. they came and asked if if the city
would have any um um trepidation with
reducing the amount of land for the uh
the park. And so I went and and spoke
with our parks director or our CR
director and they said, you know, u I
think it was a holiday park size park is
around 45 acres and that's really what
they're targeting for that area. That's
what they would like to have. So the
area um was bigger than what they
needed. There is a community group um
local people um and guys like John Good
Godina and other folks who are trying to
build an indoor uh turf facility, some
gymnasiums and things like that. There's
a a very large um club environment now
for volleyball and basketball, soccer,
and they're trying to find a venue to
help those clubs have a place where they
can practice and play their games. And
so that's what they would like to do
with with that land. the owner is
actually um willing to um she talked
about giving them that land to to be
able to make that happen or selling it
to him at a very reduced process to try
to bring an amendy like that to the
community. And so that's how the uh the
conversation came. But in order to be
able to do that, it had to come back to
this governing body for approval. And
that's where we're at today.
>> If that helps.
>> Anybody else for the developer?
>> Casey, thanks for being here.
>> Thank you. Anybody else in the audience?
Who does Jennifer?
Is it Dr. Anie?
>> Uh, Mr. Miller, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Um, sorry. Give me just a second here.
Um,
this is the
uh mayor, Mayor Collins, members of the
governing body. For the record, um,
Charles Miller. My testimony tonight is
strictly confined to the legal and
procedural um, sufficiency of the SweetG
Grass PUD amendment currently on the
floor for its third and final reading. I
am formally entering the systemic audit
into the administrative record prior to
your vote. The telemetry of this
ordinance reveals an unmititigated
structural defect. The applicant is
requesting exceptions to the unified
development code specifically regarding
block dimensions, density constraints,
and phasing. However, cross- referencing
this with the city's master plan exposes
a direct contradiction. The current
traffic and utility routing funnels
unacceptable loads onto SweetGrass Drive
and College Drive, and the developer has
not secured or funded the required
secondary arterial connections to
mitigate this. Approving these UDC
exceptions under these conditions
constitutes a systemic arbitrage. It
privatizes the revenue of the
subdivision while socializing the cost
of the traffic and utility mitigation
onto the Cheyenne taxpayer. Because this
is a third reading advancing this plat
legally anchors the city to a defective
fiscal model. I'm placing a constructive
notice on the record tonight that this
infrastructure deficit has been
identified. I formally request the
council neutralize this advancement and
vote no until the infrastructure costs
are fully internalized by the applicant.
Thank you,
>> Mr. Miller. Two things. One is it's on
second reading, not third reading. And
the second thing is all we're asking to
do is to change the uh the zoning to
allow for uh this to be split. We've not
approved any sort of development yet.
That would have to go through our
regular process, which would include uh
traffic studies and all of those types
of things. So, you're just a little
premature, sir. Anybody else in the
audience?
>> Anybody else?
>> All right. Hearing none. Uh Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the motion to approve failed
at the public service committee.
Therefore, there is no recommendation.
However, for the sake of discussion, I
move to approve on second reading.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave.
>> Okay. Any comments for members of the
governing body on the change to the PUD?
>> Dr. Ems, did you have a comment? Dr.
Aldridge,
>> Collins, through you. I am um I'm really
torn quite honestly on this because I
see the benefit um to the city of having
only a 45 acre park to care for. My
concern is that
60 plus acres was set aside and that we
would be using that excess um beyond the
45 acres for um basically a private
venture whether it be for a club use or
or community use or not. But it doesn't
give people the same access as what a
public park would have um had that
entire 60 plus acres been converted into
a park. Um, I am going to go ahead and
vote for this this evening because I
believe that um our community wreck and
events team is um stretched thin with um
maintenance and upkeep of parks as well
as there's a big need for more floor
space or gym space um in our current
climate and environment. Um, I would
hope that the developer um or the
entities that develop this, if there is
if they get to the point where they're
going to have some sort of a um indoor
practice area that um I know that plan
will be coming back before us and at
that point we can have a conversation
about access for the general public.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
All right, hearing none, we're on second
reading. And all those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And
>> those opposed. This ordinance is
approved on second reading.
>> Number 11, ordinance, second reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land west of Round Top Road and
adjacent to Happy Jack Road.
>> All right, this is an owner initiated um
annexation and uh we'll go out to the
audience. It looks like we have a lot of
people here again today. Um I do know
that u um there has been a uh um well
I'll just let let the people talk. So um
would you push the button Cindy and and
introduce yourself?
>> Certainly. Good evening Mr. Mayor,
members of the council. My name is Cindy
Delansancy. I'm a partner with the law
firm of Holland and Hart. I'm here
tonight with my client Tom Glymmeer and
Jack O'Neal um on behalf of Via West. On
April 24th, Mr. Mayor, um I respectfully
requested a postponement on the um uh
second reading for the ordinance
currently um before you this evening
with the hope of maybe having um
opportunity to work with my clients and
some of the interested parties as
outlined in the um letter to allow for
more time to develop some of the
conversations that built upon the
discussion uh in the committee. And so
with that, Mr. Mr. Mayor, um that is the
request that we hit the pause button in
a way that is appropriate under your
rules as well as um at the desire of the
governing body, however you may choose.
>> Thank you.
>> Did one of your clients want to speak?
>> Please, sir, identify yourself for the
record.
>> Tom Mcgissmeer, Vio West Group. Thank
you, Mr. Mayor. Members of the council,
we uh appreciate the consideration to
pause. We
uh believe and see it's very obvious
that Cheyenne is a very close-knit
community and we take that very
seriously and want to respect and
respectfully have the discussions unfold
in an appropriate timeline. Thank you,
>> Jennifer.
>> Mr. Mayor, I do have um Director Bloom
with his hand raised.
>> Mr. Bloom,
>> mayor, members of council, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. Um, I just want to note that
I've had some conversations with the
applicant regarding this postponement
and there have been some conversations
with folks that have been um thinking it
or thinking it may be appropriate to
postpone this to a period of time this
fall. Um, if you all do seek any type of
postponement on this item, I would
recommend that you all seek the first
regular meeting of June. I believe that
is June 8th. Um, this could allow the
applicant to forge forward with a plan
to address some of the items that were
identified at the public hearing. Um,
and if Lil's items still need further
addressing at that June meeting, we
could consider postponing it even
further. In addition, there is a
companion item that is also on this
agenda. item number 23 that's being
referred to committee that it would
allow for this item and that item to be
discussed side by side that is a land
use plan amendment. Um I'm open for any
questions that you may have and I do
know the um other staff is there as well
that can definitely handle the questions
too. Thank you.
>> Thank you Charles.
>> Miss Woodhouse, welcome.
>> Thank you. Good evening. Gay Woodhouse
for Cox Ranches LLC, which is Mark T.
Cox I Beverly Cox Black. We've been here
before to discuss the problems with the
mausoleum being on this property and
needing to preserve that. Not only to
preserve it in in situ, but also the
access to it. Uh we have very uh
received some very positive responses
from the developer and plan to have a
meeting here later this week and quite
honestly what we need it is something in
place that will protect that mausoleum
and and it can't be done by June 9th or
I mean we need some time there need to
be some surveys done there needs to be
some other parties involved with what we
need in order to preserve that mausoleum
and to keep it as it is to allow other
members of the family to use it if they
desire and certainly to access it over
the in perpetuity. So, um honestly, we
we would like something in August. We
it's going to take a while and we don't
want to be rushed. We don't want to be
in a position where we're having to not
have all our tees crossed and eyes
dotted.
>> Sounds good. I'm happy to hear that
progress is being made.
>> Yeah.
>> Question.
>> Uh, Miss Woodhouse, there's a question
from
>> Y
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Uh,
thank you, Miss Woodhouse. Juan asks,
"Is there anything in the will or any
wills that say this property can't be
developed and it must be maintained this
way?" Because I know that happens. Some
mausoleiums and final wishes.
>> Mr. Mayor, Mr. Mr. Mayor through you.
Uh, Councilman Mooney, there there was
nothing like that. No.
>> Right. Thank you.
>> If I might one more.
>> Yes, ma'am. Please.
>> Part of the issue that's arisen here has
to do with the fact that when Elizabeth
Cox uh was living on the property, her
son William S. Cox, who's also buried in
a casket in the mausoleum,
convinced her to convey this particular
property that has the mausoleum on it at
the time during her life. So that of
course she would have assumed that
nothing would ever happen to it in terms
of not having access to it or not being
kept in the proper condition and so
forth.
>> Thank you.
Yes, ma'am.
>> Would like to give I don't know who to
give this to.
>> What is it?
>> It's just my statement and some
supporting documents.
>> If you could give it to our clerk here.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening. My name is Heather Madrid.
I'm a resident of Harmony Meadows. I'm
here in opposition to the Cox Ranch
annexation. During the public services
committee meeting on April 20th, several
facts about this particular parcel were
presented that should make this proposal
a non-starter with no need to postpone.
There are likely endangered plant
species on this property along with bald
eagle and raptor nests which are
federally protected under the bald and
golden eagle protection act and the
migratory bird treaty act. These laws
make it illegal to disturb nests
interfere with eggs and feeding or
raising young. There's also surface low
surface flow from Crow Creek on this
parcel which is an integral part of
Cheyenne's water supply including our
drinking water. Even when it appears to
be dry, there is still water moving
below the surface that helps recharge
the local aquifers. Adding a data center
there will reduce recharge and increase
pollutant loading. The impact of
disrupting this fragile system will
extend beyond this property, weakening
the property rights argument. With all
due respect to the Florida based
property owner, the Colorado based
developers, and the Texas-based
operators, Wyoming water rights, our
health, quality of life, cost of living,
and the long-term livability of our
community must come before opportunistic
get-rich schemes. Another concern is
that this proposal follows a recurring
pattern of secrecy that prioritizes the
interest of the joint powers board chem
leads and their dual overlapping and
private members over the public's right
to transparent governance. When
representatives from Meta, Microsoft,
Cruso related digital and tall grass pay
for seats on the board of leads which
according to their own bylaws guarantees
influence on private economic
development decisions. The public loses
its voice. When Leeds is paid by the
city as the official contracted economic
developer while also acting as the
private land owner and manage sites they
recommend for development, meaning they
stand to profit or otherwise benefit
from their recommendations, an inherent
conflict is created. When the mayor and
county commissioners serve on these same
boards and are involved in the same
private decisions, then participate in
related public votes. It raises serious
questions about objectivity. This
council had the opportunity to fix this
in 2023, but chose not to by voting down
an ethics ordinance requiring disclosure
and recusals in such situations.
Cheyenne deserves an economic
development model where our elected
officials make decisions in the open,
not behind the closed doors of a private
nonprofit boardroom where code names
like Project Cosmo are created,
non-disclosure agreements are signed,
and shell companies like Goat Systems
LLC are developed to hide obscure
details from the public. While projects
are fasttracked on land owned by leads,
the public services committee rightfully
voted against this annexation partly
because of the impact on our water
supply and partly because the data
center component was withheld from the
public. I urge you to follow that
recommendation and vote no, not only on
this annexation but all future
annexations and resonings for the
purpose of data centers or business
parks until robust ethics and disclosure
standards are in place. Our elected
officials elected officials should not
be serving two masters. Thank you.
Folks, I'm going to ask you not to do
that, okay? Please, we're uh I
appreciate you guys love what she said,
but uh uh please
>> come right up here and have that
conversation. Uh sir, did you want to
come?
>> Good evening and welcome.
>> Good evening. Thanks for having me,
Jordan community member. I'm here to
speak in opposition to the proposed
annex. We keep hearing that this will
benefit the neighbors and the broader
community. But the biggest issue many
residents have tonight isn't just the
project itself. It's trust. A lot of
residents no longer believe their input
actually changes anything. People show
up, they send emails, they speak during
public comment,
and then decisions move forward exactly
the way they seem to be planned from the
beginning. Now comments on social media
have even been disabled. When that
happens over and over again, public
participation starts to feel less like
it matters and more like a box that just
needs to be checked. Now, we're told
that the annexation will help the area
by bringing city fire and police
services. But that claim raises another
question about capacity. The city has
struggled even to address issues like
compensation for the firefighters who
already serve this community. If
supporting the people who are currently
protecting this city has been difficult,
it's reasonable for the residents to
question how expanding the city's
responsibilities will work in practice.
At the same time, we've seen the county
sheriff's office picking up more of the
workload created by the recent
annexations. They've stepped in to help
cover the gaps, and they're doing that
without receiving additional benefits or
resources from the city for that effort.
So when the city says annexation will
improve services, many residents
understandably want to know how. That
promise will be fulfilled when the
existing system is already under strain.
Leadership requires more than announcing
projects and asking the public to trust
the outcome. It requires transparency,
honesty about impacts, and willingness
to listen when the community raises
legitimate concerns. Tonight, you have
the opportunity to show the residents
that their voices matter before
decisions are finalized, not after.
Thank you.
>> Good evening, sir.
>> Good evening. Connor Nicholas at Bud
Fallon Loftes. I represent the land
owner who's uh petitioning for this
annexation. I just wanted to give a
little bit of a background of of who the
land owner is and you know what the
purpose of of what we're trying to do
is. Um the landowner is the is the
trust. Um William S. Cox Trust. Um and
the intent and purpose for this um for
this foundation uh for this uh purpose
for the uh um selling the land and and
to be able to um develop the land is to
fund a foundation. Um the foundation is
the Cox Family Foundation. It is a
foundation that's intended to um support
local issues here in in Wyoming um
including FFA and and agricultural
related issues. Um along those lines,
that foundation um did uh support uh
Chinese East's uh efforts in bringing
kids to the FFA National Championship in
Indianapolis this last year. And we do
several things along those lines in
order to be able to develop this land
that allows us to be able to fund that
foundation. And it's it's really trying
to bring good things here to the
community. So, um, I I am happy to talk
more about some of that intent. Um, but
I also am available for questions. Thank
you,
>> Dr. Alders.
>> Mayor Collins, through you. I'm just
interested, Mr. Nicholas in the um you
said the Cox family foundation and I
think there's been a lot of um confusion
because the my understanding is the
owner of the the that's of the land is
his last name is Cox also but he's not
related to the Cox that were the
original Cox family. So is this Cox
foundation family foundation
held in trust by Mr. Cox that lives in
Florida or Mr. Cox and Mrs. um Black
that live here in Cheyenne. I'm just not
really sure which Cox family we're
talking about.
>> Mr. Nichols, can you answer that
question for us, please?
>> Yes. Uh through you, Mayor. Um the the
way that that works is that yes, it's
the trustee is Mr. Joe Cox in Florida.
However, this is due to a trust that was
created for Mr. William Cox and this was
his last wishes that were created
through that trust and so by um Mr.
William Cox his dying wishes was to
create a foundation and that foundation
is what is being perpetuated through Mr.
Joe Cox
>> and and it's running the things that
that Mr. William Cox requested
um in his estate.
>> Thank you.
>> I have a question Mr. Moody.
>> Y thank you Mr. Mayor for you. Uh, thank
you, sir. So, I'm just trying to
understand it. So, you're saying selling
this land is to benefit the Cox
Foundation. Is that what you're saying?
>> It it is to fund the C the Cox
Foundation in order to uh enact its its
goals, which among other things is to
support local communities and to support
the FFA and and local issues that way.
>> Paul, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> All right. Thank you, Mr. Thank you for
that answer. I guess I'm just curious if
that's the case then why would it be
sold say to an agriculturebased uh
company or to a government entity to
keep it preserved?
>> Mr. Nichols,
>> I think a few things that comes out of
that is um as a land owner, they're
trying to develop the land the best they
they see fit for the the uses that are
in the area and to be able to fund that
foundation the best way they can. And so
we were given mo many different
opportunities and and options as to how
we wanted to develop this land. And I
guess the the the long and short of it
is this is an opportunity that that the
foundation saw as as a benefit here um
that allows them to to fund the goals
that they have. And so that's really the
long and short of it. Um yes, there's
there's the goal of of founding of
funding agricultural advocacy and things
like that. Um, and part of funding a
agricultural agricultural advocacy is to
be able to allow for um,
raising up the next generation in a and
teaching them things as well. And so
this is the best way for us to be able
to fund it at least at this current time
and in place. And and that's really the
goal here.
>> Thank you. I have no further questions.
Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. And I don't know,
I'm hoping this is an appropriate
question. Um, so is the foundation a
501c3 charitable corporation?
>> It I believe it is. Um, the the trustee
is the one establishing the foundation
and um part of what we need is to be
able to fund it and and so they're
working through those that that as we
speak.
>> So the corporate I'm sorry.
>> Go ahead,
>> Mr. Mayor. Um, so is the corporation
papers currently filed or are they in
the works of being developed? They're in
the works of being developed from my
understanding. Yes.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir. Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you through you. Um,
Mr. Nicholas, um, so who was the
counterparty on this land transaction?
>> That that'd be Vio West.
>> Vow West. Okay. And so they're the data
center developer. Is that right?
>> That's correct.
>> I'm sorry, Mr. Mayor. I've got a couple
follow-up questions. Um, and I take it
because your
uh found your your client.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, is uh the applicant in this case
that you haven't reached a firm and
final agreement uh with Vio West to
transfer this property. Is that right,
>> Mr. Nichols?
>> Through you, Mayor. We we've entered
into a purchase sale agreement. Um, and
that's that's it. It hasn't closed. Yes.
>> Okay. And and
>> and and one thing I just want to say
first is I have to be careful um because
there's a confidentiality statement that
um you know that we're bound by. So I
need to be careful that to not to not
breach that. So um some of these I may
have to defer to to to Vio to to answer
just so I don't break that side of the
of the agreement.
>> Well and and Mr. mayor um through you.
Thank you. Um and I I certainly wouldn't
ask you to do that uh Mr. Nicholas, but
um I guess is it fair to assume that
this agreement uh between uh your client
and via West is contingent upon the
annexation being approved by the
governing body?
>> That could be one of multiple multiple
items. Yes.
um in your discussions um with VOS, did
you ever um consider with them that uh
they would be a co-licant with you on
the uh application for annexation?
>> Yeah, we were open to whatever whatever
made sense and so we we applied as was
recommended by by our by both parties as
to how we wanted to do this. So we we
have not really had any kind of you know
requirement that we had to be a
co-licant or or the sole applicant or
anything like that. We were playing as
as partners on that side.
>> Mr. Wolf, I'm not sure they can. I think
the application has to be signed by the
owners of the pro the at least 50% of
the owners
>> and that was our understanding
>> 5142. I think it has to be signed by the
owners of the property. And if you're
not an owner, I don't think you can sign
the application.
>> And that was my understanding as well.
Mayor, I apologize for for interrupting.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Just another
followup. I'm
Mr. Nicholas, are you aware of the fact
that first time we the council learned
about Via West and Skybox was a week
ago, Monday.
>> I I wasn't aware. Um, we were, you know,
we we entered into the contract and we
did not want to to step on toes. we were
involved with um with our parties
>> and and um Mr. Nicholas um mayor follow
up on this. How long have you been in
discussions with the planning department
about this proposed annexation?
>> I would have to defer to to Via West on
on that.
>> So you personally haven't had any
discussions with the planning
department? No, not beyond um anything
that was requested of us, but but these
have been done through Vio West.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Thank you, Mr.
Nichols.
>> Anybody else? M. Nicholas, thanks for
being here.
>> Thank you, sir. Please,
>> Mr. Mayor, Council Rick Kesler, Rolling
Hills Estates.
Um, recently the council president
talking about data centers was quoted as
saying, "Historically these developments
have occurred in a business park
environment which is somewhat isolated
from daily activities."
Well, that statement is absolutely
correct and it's it's exactly why this
proposal is so deeply out of place. The
property being considered for annexation
is not a business park. It's not a
vacant lot waiting for development. It's
a ranch. It's part of the historic
Wyoming Angus Ranch established around
1896.
It sits among other long-standing
ranches, the King Ranch, the Shellback
Ranch, and the Polar Ranch. These lands
are woven into history and the identity
of this community.
The proposal before you does not comply
with state statute. It offers no clear
benefit to the health or welfare of the
neighbors who will be most directly
affected. It does not constitute a
natural, geographical, economical, or
social part of the city, and it's not a
logical or feasible addition to
Cheyenne.
And in addition, the city planning
department apparently hasn't even
followed its own established procedures
for annexation.
We've learned from previous testimony
that the city purchased a portion of the
ranch from the Cox family without
disclosing the purpose. Only later did
they learn that the purchase was made to
enable annexation of another part of the
ranch. Does this reflect the western
values the mayor speaks about so often?
Values like honesty, forthrightness, and
respect for the people who built this
community.
So, let's return to the council
president's own words. Historically,
these developments have occurred in a
business park environment. If that is
true, and it is, then let's stay on the
side of history. Cheyenne already has
several established business parks where
data centers centers can be built
without sacrificing a historic ranch or
the neighborhoods next to it.
Development can happen and it should
happen in places designed for it. You
are the stewards of Cheyenne's future.
This decision is not only about land.
It's about identity, trust, and the
values we claim to uphold. Preserving
this ranch preserves a piece of who we
are. I urge you to choose the path that
honors our history, respects our
community, and reflects the integrity
Cheyenne deserves. Thanks,
>> Mr. Kesler. Can I ask you a quick
question about uh the city bought some
property in order to
um effectuate an annexation? I'm not I'm
not following that. Can you help me with
that?
>> Mr. may as I understand it and the Cox
family can help me with this. There was
a 44 acre parcel along HappyJack Road
and that's what's being used to make the
Cox Ranch that's that's proposed to be
annexed contiguous with the business
park.
>> Thank you.
>> Mr. Nicholas,
>> that 44 acres was part of an estate
settlement that was and and it's owned
by the the Willie S. Cox Trust. It's not
owned by the city. It is owned by the
Willing Mass Cox and it's part of this
application.
>> Okay.
>> So, just so I'm clear, Mr. Castler and
Mr. Nicholas, there there are some land
that was used to to create the
contiguity, but it was not city-owned
property. We did not initiate the
annexation of that. We didn't purchase
that property. No, that was that's part
of this application. It's owned by by
us.
>> Okay. I just wanted to make sure we had
the record straight. I appreciate your
comments, sir. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Nicholson,
>> sir. Welcome,
>> Mr. Mayor. Uh, Councilman, my name is
Brennon Crerache. I didn't come here
with any prepared statements.
>> Can I can I bother you to bring that
microphone up, sir? There you go.
>> Um,
>> I came here as a concerned citizen. I
live off of HappyJack Road. Um,
my thoughts on this annexation is where
does it end? Mr. Mayor, you established
a a proposal to annex uh city pockets
or, you know, county pockets inside the
city itself to uh create continuity with
fire department, EMS, 911 calls. I
understand that. If you look at this
annexation, there's probably two square
miles that butt up against the Air Force
base that are not annexed into the city.
They're still county. So, how does this
play into the city's requirement? And
where does it end?
If in 20 years we're at the same fight
in another 10 miles, then it's my fight.
>> That's all I have. Thank you.
>> Understood. Thank you.
Good evening.
>> My name is Thomas White. Um, you know
that data center that's there. How many
data center are we going to have in
Cheyenne?
You know, I speak for some of these
people here that live out in the county.
I live off of Terror Ranch Road. Right
south of my house. They drilled a well
1,800 yards from my well. I'm under
wellwater.
And that data center is going to be
south of where I live.
And you guys live in a city. You guys
don't live out there to understand what
some of these people are talking about.
My thing is
their lights are just like that
Facebook. My son lives in North Valley.
I go see him. You see that light? Used
to been dark. Nice. Now it's not. And
that's what's going to happen out there
on Terra Ranch. But like the data
center, how many more data center are we
going to have in Cheyenne? And on top of
that, if they do build that data center,
you got to consider the traffic right
now off that gley highway just with with
that data center east of that port entry
and that and then they got that Facebook
that traffic is bad in the morning, at
night. I mean, there's been already a
couple accidents on that road already.
And then once they finish the other data
center, could you imagine what the
traffic is going to be like? When I'm
saying the people at HappyJack Road, you
know, that that road out that way is a
two-lane highway. You know, if you have
that much traffic, that much employees
going in and out, could you imagine what
it's going to be like out there for some
of these that people that lived out
there? You got to consider the people
that live out there because they lived
out there for a reason. They've been
there longer than the guys that are
building the data center. That's the way
I feel. Yes, I'm Native American and I
love the land and the land that we have
in Wyoming now, a lot of is getting
destroyed.
You know, I I did research on data
center data center across the country.
People are fighting against that data
center. Some have stopped him. A rancher
I read one where they're going to pay
him 18 mil $80 million. He turned them
down. He says, "I
like my people that I live near, you
know, the resident, the people that live
there." He said, "I care for them." It's
something to consider
not jumping into it. Do a research
because I know you guys are busy. Some
of you guys need to go south to Cheyenne
in the morning at night and see how that
traffic is. It's terrible. It wasn't
like that long time ago. And then, you
know, after they get done with that,
then you they're going to be thinking
about a man camp. That's what you're
going to have about 800 guys that's
going to be parked over there somewhere.
And you when they build that data
center, how many employees, how many
man's going to be there? You got to
think about your people here in
Cheyenne. You know, I'm a full I've
lived in Wyoming most of my life. All I
grew up west of Cheyenne out in the
county all my life and I see Cheyenne is
growing. Yes. But we got to be careful
how it grows because the more This is
what I always tell people. The more
people you get, the more problems we're
going to have. That's just the way it
is,
you know. And that's
Basically what I I feel and I feel for
the people around Cheyenne. You probably
heard people around Cheyenne that
Cheyenne's we have people coming from
all over the country coming here and
Cheyenne's starting to change. You have
people coming in trying to change us
from wherever they came from. And that's
all I have to say sir. Thank you mayor
for allowing me to speak.
>> Appreciate you being here.
>> You guys have a good night.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening ma'am. Hello.
>> Okay. My name is Sue Roka.
>> Sue, I can have you bring that
microphone pointed right towards you.
>> Works. Okay. I'm sure I'm going to botch
this up. Uh I'm not I don't like to
speak in front of groups. Um I don't
like politics. I don't But I just I have
to ask some questions. One, this
foundation I guess I would like to know
more as an individual. What else is this
foundation for? Okay, I mean, it's got
to be more than just the FHA and, you
know, little projects like that that
they have. What else does it fund? And
why does it have to be funded by selling
this property? Okay, I mean, I would
have thought that other things would
have been taken into consideration. To
me, it looks like a quick way to make a
nice big buck. Um, the other thing is,
you know, okay, this foundation is
created. We have the mausoleum out there
somehow. I don't think their intention
was to look over a business park. Okay.
I I I mean, I just I'm not seeing this.
I don't think that was their intention
when they wanted to have their remains
left on the ranch there and stuff. So, I
struggle with that. Um, the other thing
is for those of us that own out there,
my husband and I just bought out and I
guess it's the Coxic States it's called,
but we just bought out there two and a
half years ago. We lived out further
west off of HappyJack. We moved into
town. We were snowbirds for a while. We
gave that all up because we wanted to be
back in the county.
And to see that this is even a
possibility
to have that taken away from the people
out there. I'm like a lot of the others
here. I don't see where it's benefiting
us. Most everything out there is four,
five acre properties, maybe 10 acres
zoned to have horses and goats and
whatever other critters that people want
to have out there and raise. What
happens to that when it's next to the
city? Who wants to buy five acres in the
city? I I'm just not seeing it. Okay.
And that's where my biggest concern is.
Our property value is going to go down.
Okay. We spent quite a bit top dollar to
go back out in the county and purchase
the place that we own out there. And all
I see is that we're going to lose money
on our property. So, I don't see how
that benefits. I, you know, as far as
the fire department and the police
department and all of that, I don't see
where there's the great need out there.
I'm not seeing people running the
streets killing each other and whatever
else to bring them out there. So,
I'm sorry. Like I said, I'll probably
botch this up, but you know, I just I I
think it needs to be looked at closer.
What is the foundation funding that they
need to sell this property to fund it?
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Emmens,
>> mayor, city council members, Brad
Emmens, uh, AVI, agent for the
applicant, the trust. Um, just wanted to
come before the body and and give a
little background of the timing of some
of the things. um one of the different
ordinances that are going through um one
of the reasons the uh business park and
data center wasn't brought up at the
public hearing was because the public
hearing was for the annexation portion
of the project and we discussed the
business park and the data center at the
planning commission meeting uh the week
before and which is also item 13 on
today's agenda. Um, so there was never
an intent to not say what it was or
where it was going. Um, we had those
discussions at the planning commission
meeting in when we discussed the zoning
and the future land use plan. Uh, we did
hear a bunch about it at the public
hearing meeting obviously and so we
thought we'd bring that forward right
away at the public service meeting which
probably caused a little uh confusion at
the public service committee meeting.
Um, so just wanted to follow up on on
the process we were following and and
when we were submitting the items.
>> Question.
>> Thank you,
Dr. Em, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins, you um Mr. Emmens, you
said that uh this follows along with
item 13, which is the changing of from
agriculture to business park. I'm just
wondering is there any reason why this
what because you're an agent for
the trust.
>> You're correct.
>> Okay. Um is there
I guess
I understand the need to fund a to fund
a foundation and to sell this property
for as much as you can sell it for for
that foundation to have the corpus to
continue on for many years to come. and
it sounds like it has some worthy things
it wants to do. Um, but I'm just
wondering
why
this it would be ideal to annex this and
then reszone it for a business park when
it seems to me that we have business
parks still available with available
space that could uh house this data
center in one of those existing business
parks.
>> Mr. Emmens,
>> I'm not sure you're the expert at that,
but you do do a lot of land use. Well, I
can I can talk a little bit in the
broader scale of the locations of data
centers in general and when we help them
come out, there's, you know, many things
they they need, primarily power, water
for fire protection and fiber. Um, and
so they work very closely with Black
Hills Energy to come up with these
locations. And so there are definitely
areas that cannot um provide the power
or they cannot get power there in the
future. And so generally um they they
look for locations that kind of have
create those criteria um to make it
successful project. Um what we found is
in primarily um currently they're
finding locations that they can have uh
large buffers. They're have you know uh
things like that so that they can have
some open space around the property and
some other things. And so that leads you
to some of these parcels um where you
can do when you get to the site plan
stage, you can create those things that
um to either try to hide them or keep
the noise away or uh anything else. Um
so I would say that's in general why we
found the data centers have chosen those
locations. I don't have any background
on the foundation part so um I was you
know that's not my side.
>> I have one follow-up question.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Mayor Collins for you. So, this property
um has the fiber, the water, the power,
and the fourth item that was the space.
>> Yeah. You know, the more space that they
have, the more flexibility they have in
their design.
>> Yes.
>> And this property has all of that.
>> Yes. And I would I mean, that's really
probably more of a question for VA West
in their final determination, but that's
what we found in in those locations.
>> Mr.
>> Yes, Dr.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So, I just want to
get my brain wrapped around this. What
we're talking about right now is just
annexing a piece of property. We're not
talking about what would go on that
piece of property necessarily. If we
annexed it, the sale could go through.
It could not go through. It could be
used for many things. It's not I mean
what we're talking about is just the
annexation not the zoning. Is that
correct?
>> Mr. Mayor you on item number 11 of this
uh agenda that would be the item that
we're discussing now which would be just
the annexation portion. Um the next item
um based on the rules uh the city has it
gives it an assigned zoning which would
give it the first zone for the piece of
property and then the next phase would
be um to get it zoned to what the uh
applicant would like it to be. So that'd
be item 13
>> and number 13 is to change it from
agricultural to business park.
>> Mr. Mayor, that is correct.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Mr. Wolf go for me.
>> Mr. Wolf. Um, thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Through you, um, thank you, Mr. Emmens.
Um, let me make sure we've got a couple
things clear. First of all, you're the
from AVI and you represent the applicant
in this case. Is that correct,
>> Mr. Mayor? Th I've been uh I represent
getting this through the city council
process for the current owner as who
signed the applications. Okay. And with
that answer and that you're representing
the applicant, you're not representing
VIA West. Is that right,
>> Mr. Chair? I via West I'm I would say in
in this case, I represent both from a
standpoint of the applicant is
requesting that the trust
uh change the zone and annex the
property.
>> Okay. So, basically, you're working
handinand with Vow West. Is that right,
>> Mr. Mayor? you via West has been
directing some of the annexation.
Otherwise, the trust wouldn't be sub
submitting the annexation
without Via West.
>> Mr. through Mayor through Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you.
>> Um, so do you know anything about Vow
West and Skybox's plans for this u data
center?
>> Mr. mayor through you. We uh have talked
about the locations of some of the
buildings, those other things as if this
project moves forward.
>> Okay. Can you speak to the water use um
that they plan at the when the data
centers built?
>> Mr. Mayor through you. Um currently I
don't have those numbers. No, I have not
been provided those. the the BOPU
requires the closed loop system which um
we do know that what that generally
takes per thing but I those if you
wanted to water use questions those
would have to go to via West and Skybox.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Wolf, I can answer that question on
a closed loop system if you'd like to
know the answer.
>> No, I don't I don't that's that's fine.
I understand that. Um but in terms of
the water use that the plan contemplates
both water and sewer that's not
something you can speak to is it Mr. Em?
>> Mr. Mayor through you we we don't
generally get into that until the site
plan stages of the of the projects. Um
and then um and again we at this point
um have not I mean I don't know enough
about the final project to to be able to
and those would be coming from their
engineers their water engineers their
mechanical engineers that's where those
numbers would come from.
So your answer to the question which is
what do you know about their energy
supplier and their energy use? Um that's
not something you've been working on. I
take it
>> Mr. Mayor through you. No those those go
directly to Black Hills.
>> Okay. Um Mr. Mayor through you. Um
>> Mr. Emmens. Um
you've talked about this two-step dance
which is the annexation
zoning as uh agriculture and then the
final zoning as a business park. Um you
have a lot of experience uh working with
the planning and zoning office. Why does
it go through that two-step process?
>> U Mr. Mayor through you. I believe the
city started the second zoning when
there a piece of property did get
annexed on an earlier item and then
voted down the zoning and so they added
this assigned zoning
um so that it could be in the city with
a city zone
>> if we had an annexation that happened
and then a couple steps later would have
been the zone change. The annexation
passed but the zone change didn't. So we
had land in the city that didn't have a
zone so we couldn't enforce nuisance or
anything like that. So, we came up with
a process to uh zone uh any uh piece of
property that comes into the city with
whatever the underlying zoning is in the
county. So, if it's agricultural, we'll
zone it agricultural. So, whatever the
whatever it was in the county, we'll
zone it to the closest uh zone that's
there um in the city. And that way, if
the zoning change doesn't pass, at least
it has a a zone that we can enforce. Um
and so that process happened two or
three years ago. Um there was an
annexation on Holland Court. um on Ridge
Road and that precipitated this what you
call the two-step dance, but it it's
important to make sure that every piece
of property inside the city has a city
zone so that we can enforce that.
>> Um thank you, Mr. Mayor. That that's
very helpful. Um you're aware of the
requirements under the annexation
statute um to make these specific
findings um that the statute specifies.
Is that right,
>> Mr. Mayor? Through you, I would say yes.
that we read the those and talk to the
city prior to submitting and go through
the discussion with um with if we feel
that it meets the criteria or not.
>> Okay. Um is there a document that you've
submitted that uh contains your analysis
under the statutory criteria?
>> Um Mr. Mayor, I believe there's I didn't
I don't believe I there's a specific
letter or anything if I remember.
Um on the annexation portion of the
submitt there is a
um check checklist that you sign off on.
>> Okay. But you you Mr. Mayor um you as
the representative for the applicant
haven't prepared your own analysis of
the statutory requirements in the
annexation statute.
>> Mr. Mayor, I don't believe so.
Um, how long have you been working on
this, Mr. Emmens, with um the applicant?
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, through you.
So,
maybe in January, January, February.
>> I'm trying to think back, but
um
I'd have to look and see when when the
initial stuffs were signed to start
working on it.
>> And and Mr. Mayor um through you uh at
the time you started this um were you
also in contact with Vow West uh about
their plans?
>> Mr. Mayor through you. Yes.
>> Okay. Um
thank you. Thank you, Mr. Evans. Thank
you.
>> Yep. Uh thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through
through you. Um I have a followup
question. My colleague from Ward One
asks, we heard about the water usage uh
power usage. But I understand we have a
tariff from the state. They have to
build their own power stations. What
current power station is out there? Cuz
I was under the impression they have to
build their own because I know that
Microsoft data center to the south have
their own power station. Are you
planning to tap into that one or build
your own out there?
>> Mr. Moody, when you say power station,
can you define that?
>> Uh, sure, Mr. Mayor. It's the ones there
by the data center, you know, the one
there off of uh by by the Walmart
distribution center. They have their
power station there to have their own
power. That's a tariff.
>> Are you talking the substation?
>> Substation. Sorry.
>> There you go. I just I didn't quite
understand.
>> Sorry. Substation. My apologies.
>> Yeah.
>> Mr. Mayor, you again I can give you a
general data center thing. I this one
this project is not that far along that
I could specifically say. Um but
generally every when they apply with
Black Hills, they apply for a certain
amount of power. They get a design from
Black Hills and then they have to build
that design. I have not seen currently
of any of the larger data centers not
have to put a substation on their own
lot that they give to Black Hills. So in
our larger acreage ones, every one of
them have had to put a a substation on
their site um and then dedicate that or
deed that over to Black Hills. So
they've all built that. So, I would
assume on this one that they would have
to have a substation that they give to
Black Hills on this. Um I believe the
substations
um that Black Hills currently owns that
are offsite or just south of I80
um just south of the King Ranch. There's
a brand new substation there um that I
would assume that that's feeding the
North Range Business Park data centers
in this one. But um again those are just
general answers to what we've seen on
the other data centers.
>> That's how I am Mr. Mayor. Thank you Mr.
Wolf.
>> Uh thank you Mr. Mayor through you. Um
uh Mr. Abs given your broad experience
with this let me let me go through the
thing about this whole process that uh
really causes me a lot of concern. Um,
so you want to separate the question of
the annexation
from the first zoning which is
agriculture
or another one and then the second
zoning which is to business park
and and in your experience as you've
seen this and as I understand because of
the questions I asked Mr. Bloom at the
council meeting two weeks ago. The
public is involved and all these fine
people are here uh because um they're
entitled to come and be involved in the
process for the annexation.
Is that correct,
>> Mr. Mayor? Thu. That is correct. And the
zoning there they're both of those are
public meetings, public hearings. Three
readings for both of those. So the
public can be involved in the
annexation, the first zoning and the
second zoning. But once the second
zoning is done and they have the
business park zoning,
that's the end of the public's
participation in the process. Isn't that
right,
>> Mr. Mayor 3? That's how for all Well,
Mr. Mayor 3u if if a platting occurs
then the platting would come before the
governing body as a resolution. So if
they decide to split the property in any
way that that the splits of that
property. So, for instance, when I was
talking about giving a a parcel to the
um Black Hills for their substation on
site, that would be a uh if it's a plat
that outside of the administrative
process, there are some administrative
plattings, but if it's plat come before
the governing body as well, I can't say
in all cases whether or not the plat
would come forward or not in front of
the governing body.
>> Um, thank you. But that's that's really
the only other after that the if you
meet the criterias within this existing
UDC those would be administrative
processes.
>> Mr. Mayor, just one more followup. So,
what I'm concerned about is that all of
these folks who've taken the time to
come here and and are concerned about
this, once the business park zoning is
granted, if it is, but once it's
granted, then the whole site plan and
all the issues with the sighting of it
and all of the decisions about how the
plant's going to be put on the property
and how many
part how many buildings are going to be
put there and what other kinds of
buildings and how the traffic is going
to go that all occurs
without all of these people and all of
us and the council is not involved in
that process either is it
>> Mr. Mayor you that is currently how the
city of Cheyenne has their development
regulations.
>> Thank you. Thank you Mr. Mayor
>> Mr. Evans. Thank you. Yep.
Ma'am, welcome.
>> Hi there. Uh, I'm Megan Plamer.
>> Megan. Megan, bring that microphone so
it points right at your mouth. There you
go. Megan Plameumber.
>> Yes. And I'm a resident west of town.
Um, and just I too did not come with any
great planned uh thoughtout speech. Just
kind of um wrote up some questions that
I had.
>> Sometimes that's the best way to do it.
Um, so, um, I'm a Wyoming native. Moved
away to Colorado for some time.
>> Welcome home.
>> But came back because Colorado Springs
was getting too big, too crimeridden,
too many things. And actually, the last
straw was
um our vehicles, the windows were shot
out. Thank goodness it wasn't the house
windows. Um, but so we came back, bought
some land because we like the Wyoming
Wild West. Um, and you know, I see
quickly within returning it's changing
really fast. Um, and actually that was
in one of the articles I read today,
that was a quote from I'm not sure if it
was a council member or someone in the,
you know, government of of Wyoming or or
the county. Um, but I'm reiterating and
restating I think some questions kind of
concerning items 11, 12, and 13. Um, and
I understand we're so only only on 11.
Um, but I just I guess I want to ask
again, how many data centers do we
already currently have?
How many are we projected to build? And
I understand with the building there's a
lot of employment, but from what I've
seen from other data centers and the
talk of the man camp uh and friends that
my son knows, a lot of those employees
come from out of state. So, how many
people from the actual city and county
are employed
by those uh data centers? And I I don't
know if you want me to keep ask or
throwing out my questions or if you want
to answer or
>> I'm not sure we have all the answers,
but go ahead.
>> Right. Well, or or speak speak to I
guess
um or or I can continue with with my
thoughts. Um I guess my other thought
and concerns were um the water and
power. I understand that they generate
their own water power and everything
like that, but um we're already in a
significant drought. Um out by where I
live, people's wells are either
completely dry. Um they're having to
spend, you know, thousands and thousands
and thousands of dollars to redrill. Uh
and what about all of our ranchers? You
know, the the true history of Wyoming. I
I saw another poor guy had to take a
good portion of of his uh cows to market
because he doesn't have the water, the
resources to feed them. Um so I kind of
feel like maybe we should turn our focus
and try and help those that are already
here. Not saying that economic
development isn't good because it is.
But I I think we should limit what
instead of just saturating
um the market. Um I also think about the
pollution and long-term health effects.
uh the noise, the lighting, um you know,
I've read several things where, you
know, people are, you know, ending up
with cancer and just all of this and
reiterating what several articles have
said that well, these CEOs of these
companies, they don't
live right by these by these data
centers. They're not hearing what goes
on. Um, other people have brought up the
wildlife. You know, we're just pushing
we're pushing them out of of their
homes.
>> Megan, we're we're running out of time.
You have one more last real quick
question or
>> Sure. Just what are they doing for the
community? How is our infrastructure
going to uphold them? And finally, why
are so many other towns, counties, and
tribal lands saying no to data centers?
>> I think one of the only questions I can
probably answer out of all of those is
uh I think we have 12. what we would
call hypers scale buildings in in our
community now. Um we have five that are
under construction and um and then some
more that are you know in the process of
planning but have not come to fruition
yet. And we talk a lot about water and I
met with uh one of the data center
companies today. You know we talk about
using closed loop systems and closed
loop systems are um uh they're filled
with
about the same amount of water that
would be in an Olympic swimming pool. um
part of it what what they call a uh uh
the facility uh property or facility
loop and then there's another loop that
is uh more towards the technology. The
technology loop has about 90,000 gallons
in it and it's filled with water and gly
glycol which I guess is like antifreeze
material and that that is what goes
through and actually cools the the the
chips themselves in the servers and then
the other about 500,000 gallons of water
um is in a loop and it and once you fill
it up um it basically stays in there
into perpetuity. um when you change your
your filters and stuff, you have to put
a couple thousand gallons back into it,
but it's about the same amount of water
is used by eight homes in a year. And
once you charge it up, then it stays
into that that area. So, um you know, if
we were to think about your wells and
things like that, if we were to put five
acre ranch jets in that area, that would
be a an impact on your wells, but as I
understand the uh the closed loop
systems, they don't have the same
impact. So, if that helps answer your
question just a little bit.
>> Thank you for being here today.
>> Sure. Thank you.
>> Mr. Mayor, just point of clarification.
You said there's 12 data centers, five
under construction. How many under
permitting right now?
>> Um, I don't know uh how many uh are
planned? I honestly don't know the
answer to that.
>> All right. Thank you, M.
>> Uh Mr. Mayor, if I may.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh just for the benefit of everybody
here, um this information is available.
Um leadeds tracks this. Uh we have a map
that shows where all the data centers
are. We have listings of the data
centers that are currently operational.
We have listings of the data centers
that are planned. And then and and and
the mayor's I mean this list has um 12
that are currently operational. It has
nine that are planned. um some of five
of which I think are actually under
construction and realize that the ones
that are actually here already are many
of them particularly Microsofts are
early generation
relatively small units the really really
big ones are the ones that are either
currently under construction or planned
in the future leads is tracking 43
other data data centers according to
their PowerPoint which they've they've
have and and handed out. Now, as you
talk about data centers, you got to
realize that data centers are both a
singular noun and a collective noun.
Data centers can define one house or
hall. the terminology changes or it can
describe a collection of halls so that
you could have two or three and of
course these as we're seeing can be
enormous 800,000
square feet. Um but but there isn't any
secret uh about you know what we have
what's planned and publicly announced.
The real question are is what is going
to come in the future.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Sir,
please.
>> Yeah, I'm Richard Lyle. I live in the
city of Cheyenne. I'm not affiliated
with any data center or real estate
developer.
Recently, there's been a big push led by
Senator Stan Sanders and Representative
Okassia Cortez to freeze
and stop the construction of all data
centers all across the United States.
Last uh March 26, Senator Sanders
introduced a bill entitled the um
artificial intelligence data center
moratorum act and Aasiac Cortez is
introducing a companion bill in the
house. I do not agree with Senator uh
Bernie Sanders.
This is AI techn there are two issues.
One is the specific location where
you're looking at environmental problems
um you know water usage and traffic flow
and whatever. The other is the whole
technology of AI. And I would much
prefer that this technology stay in the
United States, hopefully in Wyoming,
where the people who have the skills can
help us protect our freedoms and our
liberties and our way of life as opposed
to shipping it off and letting the
Chinese Communist Party do it.
Um
now I we can't turn back the clock on
this technology
but I'll there's good and bad in it. One
issue is um facial recognition
technology. It takes a huge amount of
data. There is one company called Clear
View AI. They have several billion
images in their data backup. Law
enforcement uses it and they pay them a
lot of money to identify people. As a
result of this technology, they've
identified thousands of persons of
interest and they've arrested a lot of
criminals and put them in jail.
The other side of this technology is
what they do in China and they are using
facial recognition to watch and keep
track of everybody in the country and
give them a social credit score. um
whatever. Um
another use is there's something called
a geoence warrant. That is a warrant
directed to uh a cell phone company or
to Google
for the identities of every person who
has been in a specific location during a
specific time period because everywhere
you have your cell phone uh is is being
tracked by
by Google and everybody else.
um m that may that's very helpful to law
enforcement but it also raises privacy
issues. The Supreme Court granted
certain a case like this.
>> Mr. Lia, we're times up. Can you
conclude for me please?
>> Okay. Uh the last uh point I'd say is
that Kroger's
um uh grocery company makes um over
three billion in profits. Two billion is
from selling groceries. 1 billion is
from harvesting our data and selling it
to third parties. So we need to be able
to control that by having the technology
and the people who are skilled be right
here. Thank you,
>> sir. Welcome back,
>> Mr. Mayor. Uh, with all due respect, I
think this train is run off the track.
Item 11 was to do with annexation and
it's turned into a data center
discussion. So, I think we would should
get back on uh what the the uh agenda is
and about the annexations and leave the
data center part for a later time.
>> I would appreciate that.
>> Point of order.
Sir,
>> I just exactly what Mr. Kesler just
said,
>> sir.
>> Okay, sir. Maybe I'm out of line in that
case, Mr. Mayor and council members. My
name is Daryl Ciphford. I'm a 40-year
resident of Rolling Hills Estate. I'm a
third property away from the Cox Ranch.
I'm the second property north of the
North Range Business Park. I've seen the
data center go over there, the Chinese
one that was mining uh data that the Air
Force base wouldn't allow. And then now
the new Bitcoin come in. My major
concern is water. Um I I am an Air Force
officer who was a u missile launch
officer. I saw launch equipment
buildings with closed loop water systems
fail repeatedly. Um
I walk my dogs in the North Range BISMs
Park and I've seen uh drilling companies
come in on a Friday night. drill Friday
night, Saturday, Saturday night, Sunday,
and Sunday night, and pack up and leave
Monday morning before the city could be
out there to to see them. So, I'm really
wondering if if they're really using
city water, which is available in the
North Range Business Park as long as
sewage and electricity, or if they're
drilling wells surreptitiously and using
that water without us having any way of
monitoring it. Um, so with that, I I
will yield, but I do want to bring up
that that fact. I've noticed a decrease
in my water pressure on my property
since they've drilled that well over
there. So, I think it's a real concern
and if we're going to annex something
with the possibility that this is going
to be a data center, I think that should
be a question of whether we should
approve the annexation. Thank you.
>> Good evening, sir.
>> My name is Alex Bowler and I'm a u I'm
here on behalf of the Cheyenne Area
Landowners Coalition.
And basically we're rural folks who uh
exist in the eastern half of Laram
County where the state engineer has
declared that we have a water control
issue. And I'm glad Larry has that map
because that's I'm going to tell you
that there are 13 or 14
um data centers already in existence or
under construction in Laram County.
We're the mecca of data centers. There's
one in Gillette. There's one in Evston.
Um, but they're very few in Wyoming.
We've got them, almost all of them. Now,
our the coalition's biggest concern is
the water and where the heck is it going
to come from? Uh, if you if all 14 of
these data centers are going to be
recycling their water and use about
25,000 gallons a piece, you do the math
and you come out with about 350,000
gallons of water. That's a lot of water
and it's it's a major concern. We have
we have uh got assurances from Highway
West Energy which is the electrical
supplier for most of us out in the in
the rural areas of the county in the uh
Nebraska and the Warren Air Force Base
and they've assured us that no matter
what happens, we're not going to see our
rates increase, which is a good thing.
But the water issue is really, really,
really important.
And and
Larry, I'm glad you have that map
because if you look at that map, you'll
see that there are 13 or 14 data centers
either operational or under construction
in our county. And at 25,000 gallons a
piece, 25,000 gallons a piece, uh that's
350,000
gallons of water. Quite a bit of water.
So, I I realize that I've digressed to
item number 12 and item number 13. Uh,
but I wanted to try and answer your your
questions about that. Um, and if you
have any for me, I'd be try to try to
take them on.
>> Thank you, Mr. Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. And through you,
the the coalition, they're pretty strong
believers in Wyoming property rights
laws.
>> We are.
>> Thank you.
Thanks,
>> sir. Welcome.
>> Good afternoon. Um, my name is Jack
O'Neal. I'm with the purchaser of the
property, um, not the seller. Um, but,
uh, thank you all for the time and I
appreciate all y'all taking the time to
come out. It does mean a lot to be able
to engage. And, um, I just want to
remind that we just asked for a pause
for an opportunity to do four things. We
want to engage with the community, have
conversations,
have phone conversations in inerson
coffees, actually engage with the
community is the first and foremost. The
second is really and is the most
important is to help be a catalyst
between the seller and the previous
owners, the Cox family and the black
family to come to a resolution on a very
important family and very sensitive
family issue. um and we'd love to be
part of that solution and uh in whatever
way we can between those two parties and
I think that is a incredibly important
thing for both parties to come to an
agreement on that we would just ask for
the time to help catalyze. Um the third
thing we like to do is because you are
exactly right um um uh the council
councilman Wolf that this is kind of the
last city's opportunity and the folks
opportunity to participate in kind of
what is it like to build one of these.
So, we'd like to draft a development
agreement as well with the city um to
make sure that everything is put in
place in a responsible way. Um whether
it be stringent lighting, which is more
stringent than the county, and whether
it be stringent sound, um mandating
closed loop water systems. Um I was an
engineer for 5 years for another
developer. I currently live by two of
these facilities that are owned by
digital realy. Um our facility in
northeast Austin uses about 130,000
gallons of water a year. The average
home in America uses about 100,000.
though. Um, we would not drill a single
well. We not do any septic on this
property. We would aim to fully engage
in city services and pay our fair share
as well as any and 100% um costs related
to serve the property, whether that be
for any kind of road, water, sewer, um,
police and fire services, um, as well as
just anything else necessary. And then
regards to any of the power questions
earlier, uh the state and Black Hills
Energy have a 100% mandate that none of
that cost is ever passed on to the
rateayer. Texas just passed a similar
thing. Most states are passing it. And
if not, they should. Um as a rateayer of
electricity and a daughter of a 10-month
old, I think it's really important that
we build these, but build these
responsibly. Um if not, Chinese build
about one coal plant every single week.
We will lose the AI race if we do not do
it responsibly in the free world. And we
need to do it in the free world. So then
fantastic men and women like yourself
and the people in this room can decide
how do we legislate these later once
they are built. Do we want these
technologies being used for XYZ or you
know do we want to stay in it and I
strongly believe that these should be
built in the United States and they
should be governed by great states like
Wyoming like Texas like Pennsylvania and
uh stay in those communities and be
great partners in those communities. Um
to any of the traffic issues um we would
love to do a traffic study and again
that's why we asked for a little bit of
time. Uh we will also have an
environmental study completed by next
Wednesday. Um thank you for your time.
>> Open for questions as well if needed.
>> Anybody?
>> Jack, thanks for being here.
>> Thank you very much.
>> Welcome back.
>> Thank you. I'm going to be quick this
time. Um, I just feel like in the
interest of transparency, it's worth
pointing out that the gentleman that was
I don't it wasn't clear if he was
representing by West or the the trust or
whatever, but also sits on the board of
leads and that organization AVI
construction also has representation on
the joint powers board. um highlighting
the very deep conflicts of interest that
are going on in all of these data center
conversations that happen without our
knowledge and sounds like without many
of the city council's knowledge as well.
>> Oh, got to turn the other way. Sir,
>> Mr. Mayor, Councilman,
>> can you bring that microphone up just a
little bit?
>> Just a bit. Sorry. Mr. Mayor,
Councilman, my name is Mark Eicley. My
family runs and operates and owns the
King Ranch west of Cheyenne. Um, I'm
here kind of to address 11, 12, and 13.
And I really want to talk about the
annexation because in your annexation
plan, you've clipped the east end of our
ranch, our headquarters in that. And I
think that's an unfair land grab, so to
speak. Uh, the planning portion of that,
I understand.
Our ranch isn't going anywhere. I have
two generations coming in behind me and
they are dead set on maintaining that as
a ranch. When I was a boy, there were 12
ranches between the edge of Cheyenne and
Larmy. They're five now, soon to be
four. Ours is 120 years old. The Cox
ranch is same age. I lament the loss of
that. However, I'd like to emphasize the
importance now and I have to be careful
in in my discussion with the city
because we're partners and we've been
partners on a lot of things. Sometimes
it hasn't always been great. Uh I think
I've worked really hard to to make that
a better partnership. We have the
landfill, the Sherard plant, your water
uh facilities, pipelines, etc. I'm also
a contractor with you over at the
Bellevor. So, you're on my south side.
The east side's the business park, which
we agreed to because we didn't want all
those homes built because we knew it was
a traffic, water, and safety issue.
Why is the ranch important? Well, it's
my home and my family's home. It's also
the home, and we just finished a count
yesterday with the Ottabon Society,
which comes out and does a regular
annual a monthly count. 200 bird species
on our ranch. big game, all kinds of of
furbearing animals. We allow hunter
access. We allow fishing, especially the
young folks. We can't take another hit
from you guys, and I'm not I don't want
to be engaged in a legal battle over
that east annexation. I that was a very
convenient for you to draw that that
enclosure. I'm requesting that that be
removed, our portion of that, and that's
just on the west side of the business
park. I have concerns about the the
annexation, the construction. Uh I've
been hit turning in out of the ranch of
my to no a fault of my own. People are
careless and traffic problems are a
concern. Water is a huge one uh for us.
We constantly have to drill a new well
every other or every third year because
we continue to lose stuff. We have some
that are almost 700t deep. Now, why are
cows important? This is my final comment
to you. You guys all rely on cows. You
don't even know it. Your cell phone,
your laptop,
construction of steel for cars,
pharmaceuticals,
aviation. So, it's more than just
hamburgers and steaks. That's why the
ranch in addition to history and the
folks that that have been there deserve
a shot at this or a break on this. So,
we'll probably weigh on some other
issues, but I appreciate your time very
much. Thank you.
>> Question.
>> Thank you, sir. Yes. Collins through you
to Mr. Eley. Um I just had an
opportunity recently to have um coffee
with one of our department heads who um
actually your name came up as being a an
excellent partner over the past and we
appreciate that. Um my question is can
you more clearly because I'm not sure in
looking at the map it you said it clips
your headquarters.
So, is there a parcel number or a piece
something you can direct us to?
>> Mr. Mayor, can you I I don't have the
map with me. Uh you probably have it. It
basically runs uh it actually goes by uh
our There it is.
This doesn't really this doesn't really
indicate the uh
the area to be zoned, but it's basically
south from here and it goes right
through our main portion uh right on the
east end of our portion. Actually, my
daughter's shop is on one side and my
wife's will be inside that annex.
Mr. Rammits.
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, through you, uh, I think
I Mark, did you
>> don't you mean the future land use plan
>> line? It's not the annexation line, is
the
>> Well, yes, that is correct, Mr. Evans.
And I, Mr. Mayor, through you, I'm
sorry. Yes, that is that is the correct
thing. I'm trying to bring awareness to
that right now. So, we get ahead of
traffic, we get a water. I I have the
same empathy as the Rolling Hill Estates
uh uh folks and my neighbors uh both to
north, south, and west of me.
>> Thank you.
>> Understood. Thank you.
>> Thanks, Brad.
>> Ma'am, welcome.
>> Hi, I'm Jane Lesser. I live out on Happy
>> Say your name again. I'm sorry I didn't
catch it.
>> I'm Jane Lesinger. I live out on Happy
Jack. have a property in town. Um, I was
looking at the staff report and with
regard to item number one of the staff
report, the wording says may comply to
the very edge and there there's a buffer
zone. I really question that word may. I
know things are written in wide
perspective, but I would say the
criteria for number one of the staff
report is not met. Number two, staff
report adjacent to the point but um a
quarter acre included and make adjacent
to um or that 44 acres, excuse me, my
notes acres um included make it adjacent
to. So with beyond not having that 44
acres part of the annexation does not
make it adjacent to and so that number
two of the staff report I get I feel
does not comply. Number three, somewhat
developed now. Um I think that's in
number seven of the staff report. It
says the area somewhat developed and it
would not meet future needs. They're
talking about the road and other
services. Um also does not meet the
criteria for approval. Um it also says I
believe in number seven challenging
higher level of services. there would be
a higher level of services in the area
if that annexation went through and
again I don't believe it meets the
criteria for the annexation for
approval.
A couple other items I've noticed in
people talking um with regard to Mr.
Nichols I believe from the trust the
trust he said was agricultural data
center does not meet agricultural
standards there's other ways to have
that area developed to agricultural
um to meet their
trust criteria and um to Jack that spoke
a little bit earlier O'Neal for uh if he
wants to have a community meeting I
suggest he also invite the trust people
besides the community um also what we're
talking about 11, 12, and 13. We also
need to consider item 14 in the consent
agenda as in relating to what we're
talking about tonight. We also need to
consider future expansion because once
if this annexation goes through and 11,
12, and 13 are going to be all tied
together. They're going to be like one
thing together if it's approved. Then
what's your future use for those people
in Rolling Hills? It's going to be a
forced annexation in the next 10, 15, 20
years. property values go up, your uh
equity value will go down because you'll
need to pay the own your own water and
sewer hookup unless a developer wants to
put that into their agreement that they
pay it if when it comes to that time if
it comes to that time. Um the one
question I got asked to ask is how many
data centers are just or how many data
centers are they looking at for that
building if it goes through for that
annexation. Um is that just for now or
is it in the future? Also, please
consider that Denver, Reno, and Arizona
are pausing because of water and
electrical
um considerations. Sorry, I'm getting
dry. Um so, are we any smarter than
Denver, Reno, and Arizona that we would
want something to go through? Not maybe
in industrial park areas. This is not an
industrial park areas. We need have the
concerns that are broader than just than
than uh an industrial park with
consideration for the land, what other
people have brought up and the history
of the area. And I have one thing here.
We had this flyer. It says build on
history sustained by community. If this
is something that the city is
considering for other areas in our town,
then that needs to be considered also
for their annexation. Build on history.
There's great history in that land and
sustained by community. We have
community support here not to have the
annexation. Thank you for your time,
Mary.
>> Thanks, Jane. Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi, my name is Sandy Walk. I am a
resident.
>> I didn't hear your name again.
>> Sorry. Sandy Walk. I'm a resident of
Rolling Hills.
Why is this this
coming up to annex? Why can't the county
change their zones?
And maybe that's already been
been um addressed in previous meetings.
>> Sandy, the this is not the city
initiating this. It was the landowner
asking to become part of the city. And
so, so they they I think they believe
that if they had city water, sewer, and
things that would make their development
more more successful,
>> but it's going to affect we live we
bought in the county. We want to stay in
the county and if this were to go
through, we would then be annexed later
on like many other people have said
because we would then become surrounded.
We bought because we wanted to
be able to have animals and stay in the
county. Yeah, Sandy. And I've I I've
heard that comment about being
surrounded, but that's you're a long
ways from being surrounded, ma'am. Sam,
welcome.
>> Good. Good evening, Sam Gallotus. Um,
couple comments and then I have some
questions. First of all, histo um the
foundation gentleman wanting to serve
kids, teach them agriculture.
Can't think of a better way than a
long-term historic ranch uh in Larmy
County to do that. Just an opinion. Um
number two, uh there was a a question
asked about is the power and all the
infrastructure already to the site? Um I
I believe that was answered in the
affirmative, but I don't think that's
true. probably a mistake there because I
don't think all of everything's there
that needs to be there. I think that
needs to be clarified.
Number three, um I've heard earlier on
this evening, trust, stewardship,
uh of you folks with the community and
its assets. Um, and it it brings me to
the real core of of of where I'm coming
from on this, and that is uh I read too
in the article today about uh the
comment that the everything going on is
outpacing
the your ability to plan.
And I think that's probably an
understatement.
Um but it brings me to the question when
I look at the plan Cheyenne document and
I brought this up in the public services
uh meeting it says that it's going to be
updated every five years.
The last time it was the work was done
to update it was in 2013.
It was released in 2014. And I think
when it gets to trust and stewardship,
those are documents that th the plan
Cheyenne document goes through about
community support, community input, and
everything else. So my first question is
why has it not been updated for 12
years? And I would make the statement
that with everything that's been coming
this direction over the last 10 years or
so, whether it's the Sentinel system,
data centers, man camps, whatever, it
almost seems very negligent to me that
there hasn't been a more formal planning
update uh in plan on the plan Cheyenne,
which is a joint effort of both the city
and the county and went to the people.
So, my first question is why have you
not initiated planning exercise within
that five-year guideline that's included
in your own document? The second
question I have is that
on page 17 of the document that comes
from the city's website when it talks
about the plan amendment process and
procedures,
item number two says that
if specifically related to a development
project, the proposer should schedule a
neighborhood meeting to discuss the
project with area property owners prior
to bringing the proposal before the
planning commission. Well, what I've
heard here is that it's gone through the
planning commission. I didn't get
invited to any neighborhood meeting and
I don't think anybody else did. And
that's the only input the public has is
through your plan, Cheyenne, which is
jointly done with the county. And you've
basically eliminated that opportunity
for people to give that input. So, we
aren't here tonight.
So, I'd like to understand why it hasn't
been updated because it's been asked of
me quite a bit lately and and and why
was this process not followed.
>> Sir,
>> I'm sorry, but I come to these meetings
and ask questions and they don't get
answered ever.
>> So, I'd like those two questions
answered. Sam, I can tell you we uh put
in the budget um I don't remember is it
$250 or $300,000
to uh to do exactly that to start a
process to update that. We did that in
the last um the last budget and u I wish
Charles was here to tell me when uh when
the RFP and that goes out, but uh we are
working on that right now.
>> With all due respect, it was done due in
five years. That was 2019.
>> I wasn't here then, but I am now and
we're working on it. Oh, you're 20, 21,
22, 23. And then why not the process
being followed?
>> Yeah, I can't answer that question. I
don't know.
>> Can't answer the RFP.
>> Yes,
>> Mayor Council Connor White Planning and
Development Department. Um, just an
update on the RFP. It is actually out.
>> Okay. Thank you, Sam. It's out.
>> Hi, my name is Ann Margaret Burns and um
I just became aware of this situation
just last week.
I was part of the Westside Planning
Commission committee that um helped and
worked with leads to help bring the
North Range Business Park to our
neighborhood. there were and we were
also part of um fighting many um
subdivisions that had all kinds of
problems with septics and drilling wells
and our community in Rolling Hills and
uh worked really hard with leads to make
sure that the business park was going to
be a positive thing for our side of the
west side of Cheyenne. Um they worked to
ensure um we haven't heard anything. The
neighborhood has just suddenly been um
um having to deal with this all of the
sudden after years of trying to make
sure that our community would be
protected. Leadeds helped us. We haven't
heard anything from leads either. Um um
I do know, you know, we were working
with county commission and different in
a different situation here. Um, but they
worked really hard to make sure we had
low light, we had a greenway, we had to
have trees planted, there was not going
to be any truck traffic on on HappyJack
that there would not be noise pollution.
And right now we have um we have the um
um Bitcoin operation over there creating
tons of noise pollution and the solution
that has been um undertaken is
unsatisfactory for us. We are concerned
about our quality of life. We're
concerned about the light. We're
concerned about the fact that there's
multiple bodies of water on the Cox
Ranch. What what is going to happen with
those? How are is our community or the
county or the city going to benefit from
this? Are there going to be parks put in
there? Is there going to be a greenway
put in there? These were things that we
wanted to have with the North Range
Business Park. And these are things that
they negotiated with us. And this is the
first time last Monday my husband came
to a meeting and it was the first time
we had heard anything about an
annexation and ch and it's such a such a
giant change.
Um
when are these things going to happen?
because the annexation is coming in. Um,
we the neighborhood that's in the
middle, the county, we're not going to
have any say in what happens. And are
these giant uh businesses going to give
back to the community in the area of
parks, access to maybe the lakes, those
types of situations? Why you're going to
annex and then have all this stuff done
after?
where is the talk about how these data
centers are going to enhance our
community.
So that's what I'd like to to say. The
other thing is with contamination here,
I did we did a quick quick uh Google
search on from the EESI Environmental
and Energy Study Institute and they said
that during the cooling system
maintenance procedures called a blowdown
release for a PFASA forever chemicals
linked to cancers and fetal development
cause problems in these situ in in these
areas.
And then also I just did a quick Google
search on closed loop water systems and
it says under the contaminant control
even when sealed these systems face
challenges from corrosion scale
particullet and microbi biological
growth. So there are environmental
concerns and there are um natural bodies
of water on that ranch that should be
protected.
>> Thank you ma'am.
Mr. white.
>> Push that button. Turn the microphone
on. Turn the microphone on.
>> There you go.
>> Oh, there it is. Um, forgot to ask my
question. And when they drill that well,
when I talked to these corporate before
when they were starting this thing, they
have drills through my the aquifer there
and the diagram they showed me. Let's
say the water the the water that I get
is here and then they're trying to get
to the water down below in between
there. They're going to drill through
there and go below it. We don't know
what the water's like under that. there
might be contamination that comes from
under the water mixed with the aquifer.
So I just thought I'd give you attention
that if water is fragile we can't it you
know when it rains it takes forever to
get to the underneath the ground wire
water I can't remember it takes a long
time so that's something you got to
think about like if they're going to
drill or whatever
you got to remember there's aquifer you
don't want to ruin everybody else's
water and second of all just one more
that uh you know data center agriculture
is two different Thanks. It has nothing
to relate with agriculture. One more.
The thing is I I'm an actor and model.
At times artists are upset because the
data center do
copy that's not real. If you look at the
phone, they do all these things. It's
getting to where what is real, what is
not. Think about that false presentation
of news using the data center where
there's good things. Yeah, probably for
dancing. But people will take that and
mis misuse it, make something that's
looks real but not real. Something to
think about that. That's why our country
is starting to fall into. To me, data
center is kind of evil in a way. Thank
you, Mayor.
>> Can I remind you guys again, we're on
annexation here. I appreciate data
centers and that kind of stuff, but if
we could try to keep a little bit
towards the topic, I'd appreciate it.
Sir, Mr. White,
>> through you, Mr. Chairman, Mr. Mayor
Michael White. Um,
I would like to say that I've heard more
tonight about annexation of the property
than I've heard since I was at the
planning commission and the public
service commission last Monday. Um,
we seem to be able to get more
information every time we come before
this body. Uh, and I'm one that really
appreciates that.
But I think I still feel that this
property should not be annexed. But in
alternative,
I think we need to pause on this. I
think we need to give us some time to
vote this down or vote to where we can
actually sit down
and able to address this pro this
annexation.
One question I do have is that I know
the mayor said the applicant
wanted the annexation of the ranch, but
who initiated the annexation on the
treatment plant? Was it the council? Was
it you, Mr. Mayor? Was it the planning
department? Um,
during the planning commission, it was
it was made that said that we had two
owners and two applicants.
Um, the applicant for the record under
the county assessor is the city clerk
for the city water treatment plant. So,
was it initiated by the city clerk? Was
it initiated by the council? It wasn't
initiated by the goals that this council
had for annexation in the in the in the
past. So the qu one question I do have
of that but I'm adamant about this um
annexation when we have annexation I
believe Mr. Wolf brought up more topics
that I appreciate him bringing up. We
actually had representatives
of the developer with AVI with Brad at
the planning commission. We had no
representation
of the two law firms. We had no
representation there to give us some
input on annexation from the people that
want to develop the property, but that
seems to be the process. And I'd like to
hold my other comments on what the
planning commission did with regards to
the next item. But I adamantly if we
cannot vote this down tonight then I'm
adamant about this needs to be postponed
to a date somewhat in reflection of what
miss of what Gay Woodhouse said and if
not I think this thing needs to be
defeated tonight. Thank you
>> Mr. White. I think when I said that uh
this was asked for by the the applicant
uh you're right there was a small piece
of this that is uh two pieces of city
owned property that uh I think the board
of public utilities owns that wanted to
uh to be part of the city. So thank you
sir Mr. Mayor and council. I felt like I
came unprepared and I should have
brought my swimming trunks. I felt like
I just dived into something and there
was just so much going on. Um I just
found out about
>> Can you identify yourself? um Barry
Meyer at over here in Rolling Hills. And
uh anyways, I just wanted to say that I
thought that Councilman Wolf, what you
had to say was really good about, you
know, what's this going to be like in
the future for us? How's this going to
affect us? You know, the different
things that may be out of our hands
eventually. So, I appreciate you saying
that. And um I'm just asking that you
that everyone would vote with wisdom and
look at it the right way that how we're
feeling, how the people are feeling. I
think a lot of us have really just felt
like we've been thrown into something
and maybe step back and take a little
bit of time and look at this a little
more. And um anyways um I appreciate
your time. Thank you,
>> Representative. Welcome.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I'm Steve Johnson.
I'm a county resident and I just want to
say that uh we are actually making a
pocket out of Rolling Hills. We're
starting the the surroundment of Rolling
Hills and in a few years that'll be
that'll be the annexation
topic that'll be here 10 years from now,
whatever. But we are actually starting
the the annexation the surrounding of a
of a pocket. Now,
one other uh thing is the zoning issue.
These buildings uh data centers are
unique. They make a lot of noise. They
have criteria that they're built on that
our zoning commission, we need to have
uh zoning regulations for them to
protect the people that that live next
to them. So I at this point I don't
think the city has the zoning
regulations for the unique data centers,
the noise ordinances, the water re uh
requirements, the power requirements. Um
I I think we need to step back and and
uh
look into the zoning of these.
>> Mr. I can share with you we do have
those we do have noise regulations both
for an LI which is light industrial that
says you can't have any noise beyond the
property line um and then in our
business park uh we have changed that
now so that depending on what's next to
it uh there's levels of noise that can
go on and when it's closest to u uh
residential it's pretty low I think that
number is like 50 at night and 60 during
the day
>> um so we have those things in place um
we do require
uh water um you know using technology so
they can't use water willy-nilly to do
that. Uh we have a tariff that the state
of Wyoming has that make sure that
there's do no harm to our residents. So
sir I respectfully I would disagree with
that what you just said. We do have all
those things in place. Now you might not
like the answers but we have them in
place.
>> Respectfully Mr. Mayor, I think that if
you look at uh other data centers that
have been in existence for years and
years, these issues have come up.
They've tried to address them. They put
chimneys on their on their uh noise
centers. They've done everything they
can possible. The the still these these
data centers uh living next to them is
they're inhabitable. They're they're a
pain to the citizens that live next to
them. So, I think we need to investigate
actually the nose or noise ordinances
and maybe make them a little more
stringent than what we have now. Thank
you,
>> ma'am. Welcome.
>> Um, thank you, Mr. Mayor and city
council members. My name is Minda
Bleven. I'm a resident of the Rolling
Hills um estates west of town. Uh the
proposed annexation and reszoning of the
12,200 acres west of Rolling Hills
neighborhood will irreversibly transform
the rural character of the Rolling Hills
residents of the neighborhood. The
Rolling Hills residents deliberately
chose when purchasing this property in
Laramie County. Families move here for
quiet open spaces, scenic views,
abundant wildlife. Converting this land
to business use for a data center will
destroy the landscape, block views, and
displace or severely limit local
wildlife. The increase in traffic on an
already limited road will harm safety
and diminish daily life for residents
who may rely on this road for school
commutes, work, and emergency access. I
would like to remind you that this
really is not just a case of what the
land owner wants. That assumption
misrepresents the situation. The
properties controlled by an estate which
is managed out of state in Florida whose
priorities do not align with the
interest of Laramie County residents. I
find it a bit ironic, I'm sure I'm not
the only one in this room, that the
trust is saying now that they want a
foundation to sell already labeled
agriculture land to support FFA by
selling it for business use. I I think
I'm I'm definitely not alone in the
irony there and I find it a very
miscarriage use of the foundation that
they maybe are trying to create.
In fact, I would think that the concerns
of the actual citizens of the Rolling
Hills neighborhood have just as much, if
not more, right to prevent this
reszoning from being approved since we
are the people that will live beside
this property. Citizens of Cheyenne and
Laramie County have repeatedly voiced
serious concerns about the abundance of
data centers being built in our
community over the last few years and
their local impacts. For these reasons,
I respectfully ask that the community or
the committee vote no to reszone this
parcel from agriculture to business and
to deny the request to annex the land
into the city. Thank you very much for
your time and consideration.
>> Good evening, sir.
>> How you guys doing today?
>> Okay. Am I okay? Can you guys hear me?
>> Yep.
>> Okay. Yeah. I'm I'm uh Brian Pixley. I'm
a I'm a resident of Rollerland Hills. uh
you know like have chicken round top you
know and uh I I I I live I live in that
industrial area where I hear like what
what what these people are saying like
the coin coin base things then that uh
we got that uh uh that uh computer
supercomputer center over there the
Walmart discip center and all that all
that industrial I hear that every day
every day, not on the on my uh security
cameras every night because my alert
that I has audio recorded and I hear
that, you know, like the coin coinbase,
the Walmart or some kind of industrial
thing, you know, and that I'm totally
against this, you know, against the
annexation of all this, you know, uh not
only that, but I I I personally uh came
up with the a thing called Y dot, you
know, did the the water uh water uh
drought thing. That's that's Wyoming.
That's us. We're almost in the severe
drought right now. And and if you guys
build this data center, what else? You
know, how are we going to get water? You
know, we can't get get Colorado water or
we can't get California water or
anything else. So, you know, so my my my
thing is no. End the story. Thank you.
Good evening, ma'am.
>> Good evening.
My name is Janet Tolman and I'm a
resident of the city of Cheyenne and
living in Indian Hills. So, I'm not I
still feel I'm directly affected by what
is going on here. One of the concerns I
had was someone talking about the bald
eagles and all the extinct things that
are reaching extinction here. And when
we annex that into the city, where is
that going to go?
In the past, it just disappears.
And you know, I think of Wyoming as the
land of the free and the home of the
brave. I grew up singing that song, you
know, uh, going to school here.
Um, having a great appreciation for
that, growing up and see how things
expanded, growing up and seeing how
Boeing was here and how Boeing left and
took a lot of the residents,
you know. Um, my question is, are they
going to come in and then decide that
it's something that they don't want to
have here and then they move out and
we've already destroyed everything?
That's one of my questions. The other
question is, as a resident of Cheyenne,
will I have water?
Um,
and my other concern is for the cattle.
Not just the owners of the cattle, but
the cattle. Because if you do a study on
noise,
they have a greater intensity for
hearing noise than people do.
And if they're
surrounded
by
ranches,
this industrial complex is going to be
surrounded by ranches. I think that it's
going to greatly impact
the productivity of the cattle.
Um
so um I guess that's just my question.
We are known for our cattle. We are
known for our bald eagles and all that.
If we say that's okay, we don't need
them. That's okay. We don't need
residents who've been here over a
hundred years.
What are we saying? My other question is
why are these people coming from out of
state and wanting to build a data center
here? Why don't they build it in their
own state?
Maybe you can answer that question.
>> Sir, did you want to speak? Okay. Just
holding the wall up. Appreciate you.
Anybody else? Okay,
Jennifer.
>> Uh Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can.
>> Um, Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, and specifically city attorney
John Brody. Um, today is a day of ground
truth. We are not here to witness
growth. We are here to witness the
managed decline of Cheyenne's
sovereignty. For too long, the people of
this county have been treated as an
afterthought in their own city's
backrooms. Tonight, we are stripping the
camouflage off this industrial machine.
The establishment likes to say that
growth is inevitable, but I am here to
audit that narrative against your own
laws. Your master plan, Plan Cheyenne,
mandates managed growth. It mandates the
protection of rural character and
existing neighborhoods. You are not
following the plan. You are sabotaging
it. to leapfrog over city infrastructure
to annex 1,200 acres of historic ranch
land is not a law is not logical
expansion. It is it is a predatory land
grab that violates the very spirit of
the planning documents you swore to
uphold. Mayor Collins, you told the
public these data centers use the water
of eight homes. This is a state of
technical fraud. Industry telemetry for
hypers scale facilities reveals that on
high heat days they can consume up to 5
million gallons per day. That is the
equivalent of 16,666
Cheyenne households. To frame a 16,000
home load as an 8home impact is a
betrayal of the public trust.
>> Mr. Miller, Mr. Miller,
>> in an extreme drought,
>> our state monitoring shows our aquafer
is in crisis. Yet your own agent, Brad
Emmens, admitted tonight, "I don't have
those water numbers." You are
liquidating our future in a data vacuum.
While the BOPU admits they failed the
statutory notice for a 911% lead
increase in Crow Creek, you are
poisoning the filter and draining the
well at the same time. You were told
these systems are safe, but an Air Force
missile launch officer, a man who
actually operated this tech, just gave
you the ground truth. These systems fail
repeatedly. We are not going to gamble
our survival on a developer brochure
when our military experts say it's a
failure. And we won't ignore the weekend
drillers who are already exploiting this
land while city inspectors are asleep.
Let's talk about the map, the actual
legal ordinance. Attorney Gay Woodhouse
admitted tonight the maps are actually
false. They are missing permanent
easements that won't be surveyed until
August. To vote on an inaccurate map is
an ultravir act. You are legislating a
cloud on the title. You are legislating
an inverse condem condemnation claim.
Finally, we see the truth behind the
curtain. The F RFP is out. The deal is
contingent on your vote. You are acting
as the so as the closing agents for a
Florida trust while you fund $161,826
Musco video trailers to film your own PR
sizzle reels. And when a citizen brings
up the data, when the audit becomes too
precise, Councilman Wolf calls them a go
a chat jeep.
>> Mr. Miller, your time's up. Thank you.
Uh Chris, you can go ahead and unmute
yourself.
>> Hello, my name is uh Chris Coulson. I am
a resident of um Cheyenne. Um I just
have a couple questions. Um mayor, you
made a statement and I just want a
clarification to make sure I heard you
correctly. And
um you you talked about you you heard
from someone that it was an Olympic size
swimming pool of how much water that
they use and then you gave a figure for
that Olympic size swimming pool. Um I
just want to make sure I I heard you
correctly. Can you repeat your statement
on whom you spoke to about the water
usage of a data center? Yeah, we have a
new data center being built in the
eastern part of town and during their
ribbon cutting, they talked about the uh
the the use of their water and they they
talked about the use of approximately an
Olympic size swimming pool as being the
amount of water they use in a closed
loop system. And after they they charge
that system and make it work, then after
that the uh the water use would be more
of domestic use.
in the the restrooms, the irrigation,
handwashing, things like that. Um, so
they don't um they don't use water. Um,
like Mr. Miller was talking about some
of the old style um data centers that um
used an evaporative cooling system.
>> Understood. So, I just wanted to make
sure the Olympic size swimming pool
holds about 660,000 gallons of water.
And I just want to make sure we were on
the same page talking of what that was
because it sounded like they were under
>> representing perhaps how much water that
actually is.
>> Yeah, I think when what they when I
talked to them about it um they have
they have two systems. One that I think
they call the technology loop that has
water and gly glycol in it. I think I
got that right. Um and that has about 90
to 100,000 gallons in it. And then they
have the facility pool that has around
500,000 gallons in it. So, you know,
around 600 700,000 gallons of water to
charge that system and then after that
it it just uh recycles.
>> Understood. And I understand that that
you want to talk about the annexation
and not the data center. One is directly
in result of the other. Um, you know, I
do hear what other people are talking
about of, you know, things keep
happening with these data centers. They
keep popping up, popping up faster than
you guys can make a plan for. Um, and
that's why I think people get so fixated
on data centers and the cause and effect
of them. Um, for example, with all the
the data centers that are happening
already, there's an extreme
um, semirrisis on skilled workers. I
know a number of businesses that are
electrician businesses that are losing
all of their employees because they're
getting paid by the union to work on
these data centers, which means they
can't service residential without
raising the price two to three times
because they have to raise their prices.
So there is a lot of cause and effect
that's happening within these um data
centers that are popping up. The other
thing that I I did want to mention was I
don't know if Jack O'Neal is still
there, but in Wyoming Tribune last week
he made a statement that said um
even if you guys vote no, then they'll
just go to the county. Um that was kind
of a abrupt statement that was being
made. If you guys vote no on the
annexation, then they'll just go and
still continue trying to build a data
center but through the county.
U which then brings up, you know
what, it's almost like you are asking
mom, if mom says no, then you're going
to go to dad for your ultimate. That's
not how we operate typically here in
Wyoming. Um, so I would love if he were
there to address that comment that was
made last week when they actually voted
not to recommend.
>> Chris, I'll tell you now in my life,
it's my grandkids. Ask grandma and then
come ask me. So, um, I I've graduated
from the kids, but uh, I appreciate the
comment,
>> Jennifer.
>> Uh, Kathy Sigaliano, you should be able
to unmute yourself.
>> Hello. Um, good evening Kathy Sigliano.
Um, first I wanted to assure everyone in
the room that I am not an AI chatbot as
some have assumed of other callers.
Constantly telling us to not mention the
data centers even though this annexation
is for a data center is absolutely
ridiculous. Transparency is key here and
a lot of the people don't feel that you
have been. At the committee meeting last
week, it was mentioned that notice was
given to the properties and I think it
was within a 300 ft radius, which seemed
like an a joke. A lot of people in the
room voiced that no one even lives
within that range.
You're literally just ignoring the
constituents that you represent. And we
ask that you do better or we will find
people who can. You keep telling us
about closed loop systems as if it is a
perfect script that they have given you
to read to us. Do you do any research on
this? Have you looked at other cities
and what has happened there? Or do you
just take what they are saying to you as
like a word of God? We as a community
are asking you to slow down and you just
confirmed about 20 of these data centers
currently. One of them I believe is
going to be the largest in the world.
What is that really going to do to our
community? One lady just spoke about
asking what they're going to do for our
community. Are they going to put in any
kind of parks, a greenway? Um, I say ask
them for a rec center. We keep seeing
that on a lot of community pages asking
why we don't have a a giant rec center.
I came here 12 years ago from North
Dakota where a lot of the oil field
companies gave funding to the city of
Williston for one of the most amazing
rec centers that I have seen for our
community. So I ask the these
developers,
Meta, Google, whoever is coming here, um
give us a rec center. If you want to
impede on our community, give us
something that we are actually going to
benefit from. So again, I will ask what
are these really doing for our
community? what are they doing for a
positive? What are they doing
negatively? And I ask that the the city
council really really just thinks about
this and listens to the community
members that are going to be living next
to this. Thank you.
>> You know, Kathy, I would share with you
you I think you asked a really good
question. Are we doing research? And you
know, when we look back in the history
of data centers, we recognize that uh
data centers uh caused electric utility
rates in communities to go up, that they
used a lot of water. um you know that
was impactful um and so you know we have
I think maybe an advantage of coming in
later um because we've seen what has
gone wrong in some of those other
communities and we're able to uh put
together um uh I don't call them rules
regulations requirements uh so that uh
data centers if they were to choose to
come to Wyoming would do it differently
and uh I can tell you that when I sit
down with the data centers we do talk
about that we talk about what water
being a precious resource in the
Colorado River and our concerns for that
and the fact that if they're going to
come, they've got to use water wisely.
Um, we make sure that they're
understanding the u uh the tariff system
and if they're not going to use that,
uh, we're not interested in them coming
here. We would say no. Um, so we are
understanding exactly what you just
said. We're learning from the the
mistakes other communities have made and
we're doing our very best to try to not
not repeat those and to use our our
precious resources wisely. And um so I
think we are doing that. Thank you.
Jennifer, do you have anybody else?
>> Reeba Eper, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> I'm sorry. Hi, my name is Reva Eper.
>> Welcome.
>> I'm an Thank you. I'm an attorney in
Wyoming and I have experience with the
Cox French because my family leased it
for about 10 years before I went to law
school and um we ended up not leasing it
about my the end of my law school
career. I spent quite a bit of time with
Mrs. Cox and with their hired man,
Clauddio. I even went down to Argentina
to spend time with Cladio when he was um
older and there was a veterinarian from
Cheyenne named Dr. Fox and and we went
together um at different times to spend
time with this hired man. I'd like to
make some points about the Cox Ranch,
how historic and important it is for the
history of Cheyenne. It's mentioned
numerous times in uh various books about
Cheyenne frontier days. They were uh
very successful in their raising of
horses. They raised three
Kentucky Derby winners. One of those
winners was very famous.
They um were one of the first Angus
ranches in the state of Wyoming. I
believe the ranch is 130 years old. And
in my time on that ranch, I have
observed numerous cultural uh indigenous
cultural sites ranging from tepee rings,
numerous tepee rings to what I believe
are graves and other significant sites.
Um there's also a tremendous amount of
water resources that are on that ranch.
There's surface water, there's creeks,
and in the val in the um creeks there's
also nesting birds. I observed different
plants that are endangered or um
threatened. One being the Colorado
butterfly plant and the other being the
uh youths ladies trust. Um in my work in
water law, I found cases or I'm sorry um
studies that demonstrate that even back
as far as 1967, the Cheyenne Wellfield
was affecting Crow Creek and drying it
up. And I can provide the city council
with that study. It's provided by the
United States Geological Service.
And I'm very concerned about this
annexation. It doesn't make sense for
this area. It will dramatically
negatively affect the health well-being
of the area. And um I think it's very
coincidental that the heirs of Mrs. Cox
are not benefiting from this whatsoever.
However, there are two attorneys that
are going to benefit from it. And I find
that to be objectionable that the people
that
that did this um are going to benefit
whereas the family members themselves
are not going to benefit. That's why
I've heard so much discussion of this
um foundation and I find it to be
objectionable too. I don't think that
there's ingenuous
reason behind this. So for all these
reasons, I think that the city of
Cheyenne and the community will lose a
tremendous resource if this is developed
into a data center. It should be kept
and preserved as a ranch. It should be
fixed up. It should be um cherished by
the area and it already is, but it needs
a lot of work. And I think that what's
being proposed is tragic and um I don't
I don't approve of this. So I I hope
that there is a no vote on the
annexation.
Thank you.
>> Jennifer
>> uh Maj, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Hi Mandy Shadek, resident of Rolling
Hills. I want to thank the mayor and the
council for being here today. And I want
to again give great props to my
community for stepping up for something
that they really feel passionate about
because this is the essence of civic
engagement.
The question I have is how big does the
city of Cheyenne actually want to be?
And when we say the city of Cheyenne,
are we talking about the esoteric sort
of entity that exists through government
or the actual people? We do have a
choice. We've had choices a long time
and it's been complicated. I think we've
grown bigger than we can handle in more
ways than one.
Wyoming and Cheyenne specifically has
historically been a boom or bust town.
Whether by minerals or tourism,
agriculture and the everyday man and
woman and child have sustained it. Our
tourism is largely fueled by some sort
of lost identity, one that we didn't
capture for ourselves,
but we put off in splash reels or
whatever they call it.
We have systematically to certain
degrees
created our building identity on other
places. We have taken other cities,
other buildings, and simply cut and
paste them into the landscape.
And they're always guys as good for the
people. And sometimes they are,
but we embrace agriculture as our
heritage.
And there are ways to update our
agricultural systems because Wyoming has
them at the forefront with
tagging animals to raise prices of beef
on a worldwide market.
What we can do with land that is already
agricultural
and technological
can be blended and we'll still use
water, but we can eat the returns. We
can see what we're doing and we can have
tangible output of where our work goes.
We can teach people more about
agriculture if we keep things
agricultural.
I have a problem with the fast tracking
of the building department portal.
This obviously allows people to come in
to put in
pull out
kind of like a closed system
where there isn't a lot of input but
there's always a consequence.
Even if we build data centers and all of
this stuff, we live in a drought area
and it's not just about water, but there
are heat islands and we are seeing
climate change. So, how big do we want
to be, Cheyenne? Because you're the
citizenry and you have a choice. We have
a choice. How much of it do you want to
keep wild? And if you want to protect a
legend, a legend is just the story, but
what we have is tangible. Thank you.
Thank you.
Do you have any more, Jennifer?
Okay. Anybody else in the room?
Mr. Kler,
Mr. Mayor, last time, I promise.
Um, you've already heard the technical
arguments, the legal concerns, and the
planning issues surrounding this
proposal. So rather than repeat what
others have covered, I want to take a
different approach, one rooted in who we
are and where we come from.
Like the Cox family and others, I come
from a pioneer Wyoming family. My
father's family homesteaded north of
Hillsdale and my mother's father served
in the cavalry at Fort Da Russell.
Generations of my family, like many of
yours, helped build this region long
before there were paved roads, zoning
maps, or committee hearings. They
endured the wind, the winters, and the
uncertainty because they believed
Wyoming was a place worth investing in.
A place where land meant something, a
place where community meant something.
That heritage heritage isn't just a
story we tell. It's a responsibility we
carry.
When we talk about a proposals like this
one, we're not just talking about
parcels on a map. We're talking about
the character of the land our family
settled. We're talking about the views
they woke up to, the quiet they depended
on, and the open space that shaped their
lives and ours.
Growth is a part of Wyoming's history
story. It always has been. But growth
has to respect the people who are
already here. It has to honor the
history that made this community
possible. and it has to reflect the
values that brought our families to this
land in the first place. Independence,
stewardship, and a deep respect for the
land itself.
This proposal as it stands asks asks a
long established neighborhoods to absorb
impacts they did not create and cannot
control. It asks families who have lived
here for generations to accept changes
that would permanently alter the
landscape they've cared for. and it does
so without demonstrating that the
benefits outweigh the costs to the
people who call this place home. We owe
it to our ancestors and to our children
to make decisions that strengthen our
community rather than the fracture it.
Decisions that preserve the character of
this land rather than erase it.
Decisions that reflect not just what is
possible but what is right. I ask you
today to consider not only the technical
details but the legacy we are shaping.
Let's choose a path that honors the
people who built this place, protects
the families who live here now, and
preserves the Wyoming we are we are all
pr proud to call home. Thank you.
>> Okay, hearing nobody else, we're going
to close public comment and we'll go
over to Dr. Emmens and see what the
motion is.
>> Mr. Mayor, the motion to approve failed
at the public service committee.
Therefore, there is no recommendation.
However, for the sake of discussion,
I move to approve on second reading.
>> Second.
>> It's been seconded by Mr. Crave.
>> Dr. Emmens, did you have an amendment
for the ownership?
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated April 15, 2026.
>> Second.
So we have a motion to amend seconded by
Mr. Crave and um just make sure I
understand from staffing just give me a
head raise. The difference is we're just
updating some of the ownership on the
application, right? So nothing's changed
inside the the document, just the
ownership. All right. Well, hopefully we
don't have to talk about that as a group
here. Um we're just going to change the
ownership on the uh um there's a scrier
error, I believe, on that. So um is
there anybody in the audience wants to
speak to that?
How about from the governing body?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. So, the uh uh substitute
is amended. We've changed the ownership
to the correct ownership. Um we're now
back to the governing body.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Crave.
>> I'm
I move to refer the ordinance to the
public services committee
and the committee be instructed to
report at the June 8th, 2026 council
meeting.
>> Second.
>> I'd like to amend the amendment.
>> Hang on just a second. I got a
All right. We have a motion to uh
refer this to the public service
committee. Effectively what that does is
it uh postpones this item until June
8th. Um
so um
did you want to make a motion?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Go ahead. I would like to amend the
amendment uh to change the date from
June 8th um to the uh second Monday in
September
which is what the um attorney for the
Cox family had asked for. It was for
August and so if we go to the second
Monday in September that would be give
them sufficient time.
Second.
>> Okay. So, we have a motion to basically
postpone and now we have another motion
to make that the second Monday in
September. Do we have a date on that?
>> Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. We'll go out to the audience.
Anybody want to talk about the
postponement
till now? Looks like the first amendment
would be September 14th
hearing. None. How about from the
governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> I would like some um guidance on how
much that
does does that cause problems with the
process.
>> I don't know who to ask.
How about the the
>> Mr. White?
>> Mayor, members of council counterway
planning and development department.
Should the postponement pass, you will
need to you need you will need to
postpone the next two items to the same
date certain. Um, I believe it's item
number 24 that's also on the agenda that
is being basically was on consent that
goes to public service committee next
week. Basically at the next council
meeting we're also going to have to
postpone that item which we might have
to postpone even further. Uh because
technically that item should not even be
considered or voted on until the
property is annexed into the city
limits. Um, so
that one we would end up having to
postpone further, but for tonight you
would have to postpone the next two
items. We can get everything lined up
with the postponements, but for tonight
you'd have to postpone this and the next
two to keep everything together and on
track.
>> Thank you, Mr. White. Mr. O'Neal, what
does this do to u your deal with the
trust and uh
Mr. Delane?
>> Hello there. Um,
we we could that would honestly give
ample time I think to help uh the Cox
family and the seller reach a resolution
and uh we would be absolutely immenable
to that to again help catalyze what is a
hopefully a solution to a sensitive
situation.
>> Okay, thank you.
>> Yeah, there's no concerns from the trust
with that.
>> Okay, thank you guys.
Jennifer
Mr. Mayor, I'm sorry I missed Mr.
Miller's hand raised when you went by
public comment.
>> We've kind of moved on from that. Thank
you.
>> What do you want to talk about,
Jennifer? Do you know?
Is it the postponement?
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can. Uh, Mayor Collins, members of
the city council, and specifically city
attorney John Brody. Uh, for the record,
my name is Charles Miller. I was in the
Zoom queue with my hand raised for item
11, and I was skipped or for the
amendment. Um, you told the public there
was no comment while um while I was
waiting to to speak. Um, that is
viewpoint discrimination. You can
>> give us some grace, Mr. Miller. I
apologize. We missed you. I really do.
Um, and I asked I asked for comments and
just give us some grace. Okay.
Um,
>> well, tonight the camouflage has been
stripped away. You are moving to
postpone this until September. Why?
Because the telemetry doesn't lie. You
have finally admitted what I entered
into the record. Your maps are factually
false. Your surveys won't exist until
August, and you are legally incapable of
making a finding of an accurate boundary
tonight. Moving this to September is not
a standard procedure. It is a strategic
retreat. It is a formal admission that
the paper reality you tried to push
tonight was a legal house of cards.
Let's talk about the swimming pool lie.
Mayor, you said that these used the
water of eight homes. This is technical
fraud. Industry data shows that on a hot
July day, these facilities switch to
evaporative cooling and pull the water
of 16,000 Cheyenne homes. You are asking
to liquidate our aquafer in an extreme
drought.
>> Point of order, sir. They are calling
you out of order for um not following
what the amendment is, and I agree. Um,
thank you,
Jennifer. Is anybody else?
Okay. All right. We're on the
postponement um
date of September 14th. Um,
nobody else in the audience.
How about from the governing body?
All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I. I.
>> Those opposed
I guess there's really no reason we're
we postponed uh we amended an amendment.
David, do we need to uh vote on it a
second time? Because we had an
amendment. We we adjusted the amendment.
I guess we have to vote on it a second
time, do we not?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. So, now we're back on the uh uh
the uh amendment made by Mr. Crave and
seconded by Dr. Emmens to postpone but
or instead it'll be to September 14th uh
from the governing body. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right. So, this ordinance is
effectively postponed until the
September 14th meeting of the governing
body.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> And yes, sir. I just want to clarify
that during the the uh every other week
public service committee, this will not
be a topic on the agenda. The committee
will study, but they will not be
reporting or taking testimony.
>> Right. And we'll make a make a real
effort as if there's going to be any
action to uh I'm not sure who your your
spokesperson is, but we'll make sure we
get the information out to everybody so
that you can participate in any uh
public meetings that we might have on
this subject. And why don't we take a
fivem minute break um while everybody
clears out, use the restroom, and then
we'll get back to the rest of our
agenda.
Hey. So, hey
Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to call
the meeting back to order.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to call
this meeting back to order. Thank you.
>> All right, Madame Clerk. Item 12,
please.
Number 12, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official map of the city of
Cheyenne, establishing the zoning
classification of AG agricultural NP
public for land and next to the city of
Cheyenne located west of Round Top Road
and adjacent to Happy Jack Road.
>> All right, I don't see anybody left in
the audience, but uh does anybody in the
audience want to speak to us? All right,
hearing none. Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, the motion to approve failed
at the public service committee.
Therefore, there is no recommendation.
However, for the sake of discussion, I
move to approve on second reading.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave.
>> I'd move to postpone to September.
>> Let's do the amendment on the ownership
if you don't mind first. So, Dr. Emmens.
>> Um, Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by
substitute dated April 15, 2026.
>> Second. Say that again.
I move to amend by substitute dated
April 15, 2026.
>> April 15th. Okay. I just I didn't catch
that date. Thank you. Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Cape. And again for the
audience that just changes the ownership
on the ordinance. Nothing changes. Um
anybody in the audience?
>> How about from the governing body?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor please
signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed? Okay. The substitute is
approved. Mr. Cret.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, I move to refer the
ordinance to the public services
committee and the committee be
instructed to report at the September
14th, 2026 council meeting.
>> Second.
>> September 14th.
>> Yes. And that was seconded by Dr.
Aldridge. Got to get all my notes here.
All right. Anybody in the audience want
to speak to the effort to uh basically
postpone this until September 14th?
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, are you on the effort to
postpone?
>> Yeah. Yes. Uh, Mayor Collins, City
Attorney Brody, for the record. Charles
Miller, I'm speaking now because the
procedural integrity of this entire
session has been permanently
compromised. Before we advance any
further in tonight tonight's agenda, I'm
entering a formal notice of procedural
>> contamination order. Mr. Mayor, what
does this have to do with the uh delay?
>> Um the
I find you out of order, Mr. Miller.
>> The the le Mr. Mayor.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Um sorry, Mr. Mayor, through you,
Charles Miller. For the record, uh, the
legal authority of this council to
execute item 12 is directly tied to its
adherence to due process in the first
amendment because you actively engaged
in viewpoint discrimination prior to the
recess.
>> Point of order, Mr. Mayor. Why does this
happen?
>> Mr. Miller, this has nothing to do with
a postpone. But before again, sir, I
find you out of order. U Thank you.
>> Anybody else?
>> All right. Um, we have a motion to
postpone until September 14th. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed.
>> All right. We're going to sign this to
the public service committee and have
them uh work this until September 14th.
Um and that will be Dr. Rainey voting
no.
>> No, I think we had a motion to postpone.
It should be done, right? Yep. Item
number 13, please.
>> Actually, Mr. Mayor, you didn't have any
discussion on the postponement.
>> You know, I apologize. Would you like to
discuss it?
Yeah, I just I want to explain my
notebook. I don't I mean we talked
briefly.
I understand postponing the
um the annexation and and referring that
to public service committee and the
public service committee is supposed to
work that out and sort it and um
kind of monitor the negotiations between
the parties involved. But I don't think
that was the question was the
annexation. To me, the um zoning is an
entirely different matter and I'm not
sure that it is the purpose. It was the
intent for the public service committee
to sort out the zoning as well. So, I
just think it should be handled
differently if we either um postpone it
every two weeks like is our normal
routine or we kill it and bring it back,
you know, shortly before the September
date. So, um, I just don't think how
we're handling it in the case of the
zoning is appropriate.
>> Thank you, Dr. Rainey. Madame Clerk.
>> Number 13, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located west of
Round Top Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road from AG Agricultural to BP Business
Park.
All right, we'll go out to the audience
and see if anybody wants to talk about
the zoning. Um,
is that Mr. Miller again? Okay,
Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> Yep. If you're on the zoning, we're
we're here for you, sir.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, city council, and
city attorney Brody. For the record,
Charles Miller, we're on number 13. Is
that correct? Item 13. Um, I'm speaking
directly to item 13, the amendment to
the official zoning map. Um, what this
council is attempting to do right now is
the definition of illegal project
segmentation. Just moments ago, you were
forced into a September retreat on the
annexation because your own applicant
council admitted the boundary maps are
factually false and will not be surveyed
until August. I want the city attorney
to put this on the record. How can this
council legally vote to change the
zoning classification of a boundary that
you have just admitted does not legally
exist yet? You are attempting to zone a
phantom map. Dr. Renie just pointed out
this exact procedural absurdity. You
cannot sever the zoning from the
annexation when the foundational
geography of the project is currently
illegally void. Pushing a business park
zoning designation forward while the
actual land capture is trapped in a
130day technical audit is an ultravirus
act. zoning this land for hyperscale
industrialize
realize our next step is going to be to
postpone it so it matches the annexation
correct so we're not
>> we're not voting on it
>> we're not voting on it tonight we're
just it's the first step in the process
and again sir I where where did we say
that we're our maps were incorrect
>> um can you can you can you share with me
where where our maps are incorrect
>> I'm going to uh go ahead and continue
here
>> Mr. Miller Mr. I'm asking you a
question, sir. Can you tell me because
you just made an accusation that our
maps are incorrect and I sat here for
the last 3 hours. I took notes on
everything. I did not write down once
that our maps were incorrect. Where did
you find that?
>> Uh, can you hear me?
>> I can hear you, sir. And I'm asking a
question, asking looking for your
answer.
>> You said that our maps are incorrect.
Our boundaries are incorrect.
>> Um, yes, Mr. Mayor. I will share exactly
where earlier in my in this very session
it was admitted on the record by the
applicant's representatives that the
final boundary surveys will not be
completed until August. By definition,
if the land is not fully surveyed until
August, the map sitting in front of you
tonight is legally incomplete and
factually inaccurate.
>> Sir, that is not accurate. Mr. Mr.
Miller, that is not accurate. What he
said was that they are going to work on
trying to address the mausoleum uh
challenge that's going forward and they
wouldn't be able to get that done until
August. But the boundaries of the
annexation are in fact accurate and we
can move forward on that.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, you asked me a question
and I'm answering it. You're not telling
me you're wrong survey data.
>> You don't have the August survey data.
Therefore, your map is incomplete.
>> No, sir. It's not.
>> I I claim my time.
>> Please do.
>> Jennifer, is there anybody else?
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak?
>> Sir,
Jim Cher uh ward one just in support of
the governing body. My understanding was
to postpone this to September to give
the attorney the times that they could
do that research on that. So I agree
with you that Mr. Miller has been quite
a bit out of order on this. I don't
agree with the u changing of it, but
that'll all be taken care of in
September. But as a member of the
audience, I understood it to be the
postponement to give the Cox family time
to go and uh deal with the masala.
>> Thank you, Jim. Appreciate that.
Is that what you wanted to say, sir?
>> Mayor through you, Conor Way Planning
Development Department. I just wanted to
clarify that we do have a legal boundary
for everything for the annexation. uh
what was being discussed by the
applicant is after the annexation then
they can survey it but there is a legal
boundary description and that is what is
in the ordinance and that is what is on
the survey map so we have a legal
boundary to annex um this area
>> understood thank you Mr. White all right
hearing nothing more from the uh from
the audience Dr. Emmens
>> Mr. Mayor, the motion to approve died
due to a lack of a second at the public
service committee. Therefore, there is
no recommendation. However, for the sake
of discussion, I move to approve on
second reading.
>> Seconded by Dr. Aldridge, Mr. Craig.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to refer the ordinance
to the public services committee and the
committee to be instructed to report at
the September 14th, 2026 council
meeting.
>> Second.
All right. It's been moved by Mr. Crave,
seconded by Dr. Aldridge to move this to
September 14th. We'll go out to the
audience and if Mr. Dr. Renie would like
to u address that or if anybody else
would like to address it.
>> No,
>> Mr. Mayor, I will vote no for the same
reasons. And I think the fact that we
all know that
um you know, first of all, we know it
has to be assigned an egg zone on the
last action. So,
um, because that matches what it
currently is. So, there's really no
question on that on that one. And
actually, that one probably should have
been voted down. This one at least I
suppose we have the options even though
we know the request is going to be for a
business park zone. We probably would
have the option to give it LI or
something else, but I'll still be a no
for the same reasons.
>> Thank you, Dr. Rainey
Jennifer.
>> Oh, boy.
Mr. Miller, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, are you on the postponement?
>> Uh, yes.
>> Okay, go ahead.
>> Um, Mayor Collins, City Council, for the
record, Charles Miller, I want the audio
record to immediately refle reflect the
profound admission just made by
Councilman Reie. Um he he just correctly
stated that this land must be assigned
an AG zone because in his exact words
that matches what it currently is. He is
acknowledging the ground truth. This is
1200 acres of historic Wyoming ranch
land. It is not an an industrial park
and you cannot arbitrarily zone it into
one while ignoring the physical
limitations of our aquifer. When your
own council members are looking at this
proceeding and stating that one probably
should have that that one probably
should have been voted down, it proves
the internal technical review has
completely fractured. You're attempting
to overwrite a functioning agricultural
ecosystem with a hypers scale industrial
zoning designation that carries a
verifiable 16,000 home water deficit in
an in an extreme drought. D3. Dr.
Raineia is exactly right. The zoning
must reflect physical reality, not a
developer. We're on the postponement.
Out of order again.
>> My whole council is saying point of
order. Mr. Miller, you're not on the
postponement. You need to tell ChatGBT
you got to get focused on what we're
talking about here.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> I'm sorry. Hello.
>> Hello. We're here.
>> We're on the postponement, so you have
to stay focused on that.
>> That was classic.
Uh, you cannot point of order a physical
reality. Whether we are on an amendment,
an annexation, or a zoning change, the
foundational legal requirement remains
the same.
>> Mr. Miller, again, I've got a motion in
a second to call you out of order. And I
agree, sir. You're out of order. You're
not following our procedures. And I'm
sorry, I can't call you out of order
again.
>> If you want to talk about the
postponement, I'm I'm open to it. But if
you want to assault the city council or
or to talk about other issues, this is
not the time or place for it. I formally
object to the second arbitrary point of
order used to silence my testimony
tonight.
Um, let the record reflect that the
administration immediately cut my
microphone the second I pointed out that
Councilman Renie publicly validated my
audit regard regarding the A zone. You
cannot use parliamentary procedure to
suppress the ground truth that the land
is agricultural. The water deficit is
16,000 homes. The map is
>> Again, Mr. Miller, you're out of order.
Let's go on to the next person, please.
Jennifer, who else do you have?
>> Chris, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Welcome, Chris.
>> Hello. Um,
I'm I'm sorry, guys. And I I don't want
to be out of order or anything like
that, but maybe it might make a little
sense if maybe this previous person that
was speaking doesn't understand um why
they're out of order. He did seem to
bring up a good point. Um, and I don't
know if, you know, this is the first
time I've ever attended one of these, so
I do not know if um, this is not
discussion of the the first point that
he made can't be discussed.
>> Which which was that, Chris?
>> I'm sorry,
>> Chris. Which point was it that he made
that you thought was appropriate? Um
well he he mentioned that the current
land is zone agricultural
and I just uh maybe if that could be
answered maybe he would stop asking that
question.
>> Well it does it says it right in the uh
um the entitlement. It says amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne changing the zoning
classification west of Roundtop Road and
adjacent from agricultural
AB um AG agriculture to business park.
We recognized that when we first read it
into the record, we know that it's
agricultural today and the motion that
this item has would be to change that to
a business park. Um, and and Robert's of
order talks about we have to follow
whatever the motion is. And right now
the motion is to postpone this to
September 14th. So, anything not related
to a postponement is out of order. And I
I we're trying to help him understand
that, but he's not he's not following
the rules of order. Does that make
sense, Chris?
>> No, it definitely does. It's perhaps
maybe he now understands. Like I said,
maybe he's new like I am. I didn't I
don't know any of the rules or anything.
>> Chris, I can tell you Mr. Miller calls
all the time. He understands the rules.
Um or or he just he's just not following
them. And that's just disappointing.
>> Gotcha. So asking any questions about
zoning would be out of order, correct? I
don't want to waste anyone's time and
ask questions that will not, you know,
does not help anything. Chris, that
would be right because we we opened it
up for discussion on the main motion.
Nobody uh spoke about it. Um and then we
had a motion to uh amend and now we're
now we're we're focused on the motion to
amend which is the September 14th date.
So I I appreciate that you're new, but
uh um there was the first opportunity
was there and and that's been exhausted.
>> Completely understood. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Jennifer. Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none. Um, we have a
motion and a second those on the
governing body to talk about postponing
until September 14th. Mr. White, did you
have a comment, sir?
>> N.
>> Anybody else?
>> All right. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed? We have unanimous mo. Oh,
we I had a unanimous. Dr. Rainey is a
no. We have a an approval to postpone
until September 14th, 2026.
>> Number 14. Ordinance first reading
amending enforcement and permitting
requirements related to oversized
vehicles and making conforming
amendments.
>> We'll send this one to the finance
committee.
>> Number 15, resolution approving a
proposition to impose the 1% specific
purpose sales and use tax in Laramie
County, state of Wyoming for the
exclusive purpose of funding specific
purposes for specific amounts. The
proposition is to be voted on at the
election to be held on August 18th,
2026.
>> All right. This is an opportunity for
anybody in the community to talk about
the countywide resolution to uh uh
create the ballot that'll go before the
voters.
Anybody in the audience
hearing? None. Uh Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt an ISO
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir. Yep. Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Three, just a point information so the
public understands. So, this language
that we're going to approve tonight,
this will be the ballot language in
August.
>> That is correct, sir.
>> All right. Thank you,
>> Mr. Labour.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, the reason I
asked this to be called off the consent
agenda is it it is not a routine item as
the consent agenda is uh alleged to be.
This you couldn't have anything more
important than this.
This is our lifeblood. This our future.
And I really think that that some of the
discussion that's happened here tonight
and some of the attitudes that have been
displayed
really take us away from the really
important and worthwhile efforts that we
put into making this ballot and making
sure that people understand it and
hopefully support it. So I I really,
Mr. Mr. Mayor, I just believe that the
way this meeting's gone and some of the
things that have been said really don't
reflect the professionalism
and the attitude that we need to display
to the public so that they understand
what we're doing here and why we're
doing it and how important it is that we
get out and really communicate about
this allimportant ballot. So that's the
reason I asked to have it pulled off the
consent agenda. It is not a never was
never could be a routine item. Thank
you.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Hearing none. All those in favor of the
six penny language, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed. The resolution is
adopted.
>> Number 18. resolution approving an
increase of the budget of the Cheyenne
Downtown Development Authority for the
fiscal year beginning July 1st, 2025 and
ending June 30th, 2026.
>> All right, we have a motion um or a
resolution to uh change the budget for
the Downtown Development Authority.
Anybody in the audience want to speak to
that?
>> Sophia.
>> Good evening. Sophia Maize, executive
director of the Downtown Development
Authority. Um, there are no changes from
my presentation to finance committee.
This is simply a an increase in the
overall budget. We were um gotten a lot
more things done than we had planned on
when we first started this. I did want
to clarify that um after the finance
committee I had clarification from the
city treasurer and attorney that my uh
interpretation of every time we amend
our budget would be taken to the
governing body but in fact that's only
material amendments such as an increase
to the budget. Thank you.
>> Thank you ma'am.
>> I have a question.
>> Hey Sophia, don't run away. I think a
couple people might want to talk to you.
At least I'm I'm hearing that. Dr.
Emmens. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, so
since we have or since we are in the
process of expanding the borders of the
DDA, does that also mean there will be
more revenue brought in to your budget?
>> Miss Mace,
>> Mr. Mayor, through you. Um, yes. Would
that would increase um the mill levy,
whatever the assessed value is of that
property that's being included.
>> Dr. If I remember correctly, those those
property owners pay 20 mills more than
an average uh business downtown would
be. And so the next time they pay
property taxes, there will probably be
an increase.
>> And that was my next question is when
would that actually be realized?
>> Madam Treasur, do you know um
will it will it will it hit the next um
if as long as it's done by December,
right? It it's effective on the next
year.
>> It will be the next year.
>> Yep. Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Yes, Mayor Collins, through you. I I
want to make sure that I understood this
correctly. My understanding was that the
we were being asked to approve an
increase of the budget um for the fiscal
year beginning July 1st, which was last
year, through June 30th of 2026. And it
was primarily because of a communication
plan that we did not previously approve.
>> Miss Mason,
>> mayor through you, the communications
plan line item was on the budget that
the governing body did approve. We were
we had not appropriately
um assessed how much that would be. And
uh with the proposals that we received,
we decided or the board decided that we
wanted a much more comprehensive
communications plan versus a simple
website update or or whatnot. Um that we
were planning to stay within our budget
for the fiscal year. Um but we did want
to increase in order to be able to uh
provide more grants and and whatnot for
the community.
>> So as a followup, mayor.
>> Yes, ma'am. um through you. So the uh
the amount that was expended for the
communication plan um that amount
if I am understanding correctly exceeded
what the amount was that was budgeted
and I we that's correct
>> Mr. Mayor through you that is correct.
So, Cifid is the the bid you got back or
the desire what you desire to do was
more expensive than what you'd
originally budgeted and so you're
looking for more revenues to cover the
cost of this enhanced program.
>> That's correct, Mayor.
>> Okay, Dr. Al.
>> Yeah, as a follow-up, mayor. So, my
understanding is that this is basically
retroactive because the money has been
obligated by the DDA. And so, I was at a
meeting uh this week. Oh my gosh, maybe
it was last it was last week. It's they
all run together after a while was last
week with downtown business owners who
are basically um a group that has
started and is doing a communications
plan
uh
actually relatively inexpensively
through their membership and through
their board. it seems to be a duplicated
effort. And so for that reason, I'm
going to be a no vote tonight because I
really believe that um this is not
um was the people who are paying this um
extra 20 mills um
asked did not want the communication
plan that has been done by the DDA uh to
the extent that it was done and they've
gone out now and done something on at
their own Um, so for that reason, I'm
going to be a no vote tonight.
>> Sophia, can you explain to us the
difference between what the foundation's
doing and and what you guys are doing?
>> Mayor, my understanding, um, we're not
in a lot of communications with that
group, unfortunately. Um, so that was
news to us at that meeting that they
were duplicating efforts. However, the
Downtown First, as they're calling
themselves, they were formerly the
Downtown Development Foundation. um they
have a board member that has a marketing
firm that's giving in kind contribution
for that communications. I'm not
familiar to the extent that their
communications what their communications
plan will be. Uh I do know that they're
going to have a website. I believe
they're planning on doing some
marketing, but I also know that they
have done some marketing co-op efforts.
Um, so what our communications plan is,
it's a communications plan for what our
organization does as a as an authority
and what programs we offer and things
like that. And then it's also to be able
to promote downtown as a district as a
whole. Um, what that includes is a
communication strategy of how we talk to
different target audiences such as the
council, such as investor, property
owners, business owners, and then the
general public about what the DDA is
doing as well as what the what's going
on in the downtown district. Um, that
also includes a new website with all of
those resources, um, as well as what's
happening downtown. And then that will
also include a downtown promotional
video um with drone footage, things like
that that West Edge um the firm that's
doing our our communications plan is
very good at. Um in terms of what
Downtown First is able to provide, I
have no idea, unfortunately. Um but we
believe as a board that this was
this was something that we heard over
and over again from this group
specifically. And so that's why in my
opinion why it was um believed to do
something so comprehensive to provide
what they were asking for from the
Milwaukee funds.
>> Collins for you.
>> I would just like to point out that um
the downtown first group as you pointed
out has a board member that is in
marketing and is willing to do this in
kind. And uh West Edge is also one of
your board members. In fact, your board
president, correct?
>> No. Mayor through you. Uh
>> yes, David Tubner is our board
president. He's with the warehouse 21.
>> Okay. So, it is a different entity than
what he is currently involved with.
Thank you.
>> Sophia, would you also say that one of
the communication thing you're trying to
do is communication to the members um of
the district?
>> Uh mayor, uh we do not have members. Um
we're not a membership organization, but
we do have stakeholders. And
>> that was the word I was looking for.
Thank you.
>> Uh yes. So we that is a huge effort on
our part. One thing we heard over and
over again
from when I've started last March even
even now um that people don't understand
what's going on or they don't hear
what's going on. Our communication
efforts have increased substantially
from last year. Um and part of that is
implementing this plan. Even though it's
not complete yet, we have a lot of
assets to implement. Um, so yes, this
communications plan is not only to
promote downtown, but also to share with
our stakeholders what's going on in an
effective way that they can resonate
with.
>> Thank you.
>> Anybody else for Sophia?
>> Question,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh, thank
you, ma'am. I won't ask the same
questions finance committee, but I'm
just looking on uh this page right here.
Uh, the public's uh wants to see it. It
says 775 COVID rental assistance
program. Just curious why it's still
there. I mean if it was 2023 absolutely
understand but why is it still there as
6 years later?
>> Sophia
>> mayor through you uh that the co rental
assistance program from my understanding
and looking at historical documentation
that was originally
granted from the city to the
downtown business collective and then
once the business collective went
through one of its iterations it was
given to the downtown development
authority. um with the shifts in where
the organization has been independent
visit Cheyenne and now with the city um
there's been a lot of turnover and
therefore there hasn't been a lot of
focus on that program. That program
however has been completely um the grant
funding has been completely dispersed
and will be completed. There were a
couple of extensions with the our
contract with the city of Cheyenne and
that extension ended will end June 30th
of of this year. So, we are in
compliance.
>> Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I was also at
that m that U meeting that Dr. Aldrich
talked about and what I heard them say
as far as communication or at least the
way I perceived it is that what DDA is
doing is more of a macro perspective and
the DDF is doing more of a micro
perspective as far as specific events
that are happening more like weekend by
weekend as oops as opposed to more of a
a big picture. this is what we're trying
to do going forward and big picture. So,
>> so are they more complimentary then? Is
that what you're saying?
>> Yeah, I see them very much as
complimentary.
>> Thank you. Okay, Jennifer, who do you
got?
>> Uh, Alan Sheldon, you can unmute
yourself.
>> Mr. Sheldon, I haven't heard from you
for a while. How are you?
>> Yeah, good. Hope you guys are well. Uh,
Sheldon, ward two. Um, yeah, I just
didn't want to speak on the other stuff
since everyone else was speaking. Uh,
but on this one, I do just want to make
a brief comment um that I would urge you
guys to not support uh this budget
increase. Thank you,
>> Jennifer. Who else do you have?
>> Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller, can you hear me?
>> Yes. Mayor Collins, Council, for the
record, Charles Miller, I'm speaking to
the administrative standards and fiscal
integrity of item 18. The speaker just
admitted on the record that a 2023 COVID
program years after the pandemic remains
on the DDA books because there has been
a lot of turnover and not a lot of focus
on maintaining the fiscal record. This
is a staggering admission for an entity
requesting a budget increase. If this
administration cannot maintain focus on
a simple rental grant due to turnover,
how can the public trust the accuracy of
the DDA's new macro communications plan?
You're asking the property owners of the
downtown district to pay a 20 mil levy
to an organization that admits it loses
focus on its own programs.
Administrative turnover is an ex is an
explanation for failure, but it is never
a justification for a bud budget
expansion. Sophia, if the DDA's standard
for focus allows dead programs to haunt
the budget for years, why should this
council authorize more funding for a big
picture perspective when the details are
admittedly being ignored? To the
council, are we voting to fund uh
duplicated efforts and lack of focus, or
are we going to demand the DDA clean its
own house before expanding its reach?
Accuracy is not optional. I urge a no
vote on this budget increase until the
DDA can demonstrate it it can maintain
its own historical record without
blaming its failures on staff turnover.
Telemetry is truth. Thank you.
>> Anybody else?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. Emits.
>> Mr. Miller, I have a question for you
since you just spoke with us. What is
your background?
>> Mr. Miller, is he still there? Jennifer,
Mr. Miller,
>> he should be able to unmute himself.
He's able to do so.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yeah. Did you hear the question, sir?
>> Yeah. I'm I'm just I'm just curious what
the relevance is there, but uh but it's
in it.
>> Well, you Okay. Because you seem to know
an awful lot about an awful lot of
subjects. So, I was just trying to kind
of nail down where your actual area of
expertise is so that we can give it more
weight. I also would invite you to come
visit with us in person. I think it'd be
great if you would come down to one of
our meetings and participate with us
rather than doing it on f on the phone.
I think it might help us have better
communication. So, thank you.
>> Can you hear me? I can
>> Oh uh you okay um Dr. Emmens. Uh just to
expand here, my background is in systems
architecture and information technology.
In my field, we don't look at subjects.
We look at data integrity. Whether it's
a DDA budget, a boundary map, or a
hydraological load, the logic is the
same. If the input is high fidelity, the
output is reliable. If the input is
approximate or unserveyed, the system
fails. I'm not here as a subject matter
expert in marketing or ranching. I'm
here as a technical auditor pointing out
that the city's system of record is
currently broken. We have a budget with
six-year-old COVID ghosts. We have
annexation maps with no surveys. We have
a water deficit with no telemetry. My
background allows me to see the systemic
failure across these departments. I'm
simply asking the council to adopt a
standard of technical accuracy that
serve survives a basic audit. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Anybody else in the audience?
Hearing none. Mr. Escoel, may we have a
motion? Sir,
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to adopt and I so
move. Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Comments from the
governing body.
All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> All right. Mr. Hammoody, Mr. Leborn, and
Dr. Aldridge are nos. The resolution is
adopted.
>> Next item is number 22 on page four.
Resolution amending city provided health
insurance related benefits for specified
permanent part-time city employees and
members of the city council of the city
of Cheyenne.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience want to speak to this item?
>> Hearing none. We'll go to Mr. Escoel.
>> Jennifer's got her hand.
>> Oh, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Alan Sheldon. You should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Yeah. Thanks, Alan Sheldon. uh W two. Um
I was just looking over this thing and
um based on what I see um I think it
seems like a good bill. I almost wish
you guys would extend it to uh other
people.
>> Thanks, Mr. Sheldon.
Anybody else?
>> All right, Mr. Escoel.
Mr. Mayor, the motion to adopt died due
to a lack of a second at the finance
committee meeting. Therefore, there is
no recommendation. However, for the sake
of discussion, I move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody.
>> Comments from members of the governing
body.
>> Sir,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. Um
this uh resolution I brought forward
because I wanted to um make sure that
our first and foremost that our
part-time employees uh would have the
same access to um health insurance that
our city council members afford
themselves of um the health insurance
benefits. I know that we've had comments
made that uh no one would want to pay
for their own health insurance if they
had to pay for uh not only their portion
their monthly m amount but also their uh
the portion that the city pays. I would
beg to differ that I believe that there
are individuals in our employment that
are permanent part-time employees
working between 20 and 30 hours who of
which there are 19 as uh noted by our HR
department that would be willing to um
access our city health insurance um just
like they would if they went out to the
public marketplace. Um, I don't believe
that this um this this resolution also
calls for city council members um that
would be elected in the next round
because we're not able to do anything
that uh currently impacts the those that
are currently sitting. Um um but after
the next election um people who would be
elected would have access to city health
insurance um provided that they pay
their um portion of the insurance rate
as well as what the city's um share of
that is. This this actually equals um
almost $100,000 each year um that the
city pays on behalf of um council
persons and um their families. Um while
the council members do pay right now um
my understanding is $23 roughly. Um the
city is picking up about $1,850
um of the other side of that insurance.
Um, this resolution would have that
access that benefit be accessible to
city council members and their families
um going forward um if there it were no
cost to the city. So um I would urge you
to consider this as um something that
would be offered to our permanent
part-time city employees and also to
those who are elected in the future.
>> Anyone else in the governing body? Mr.
Mayor,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> I would call a question.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> Question's been called and seconded by
Mr. Crave, seconded by Dr. Emmens.
That's non-debatable. Um, so the motion
to um call the question. We'll
if it's successful, we'll just go
straight to the vote. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. So, the question has been
called. We'll go right to the vote. All
those in favor of the resolution, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. I. Those opposed?
>> No.
>> The resolution fails with Dr. Emmens,
Mr. Wolf, Mr. Caggrave, myself, Mr.
Leborn, Mr. Escoel, and Mr. White all
voting no. Next item, please.
>> Next item is number 29A on page five.
purchase and sale agreement between the
city of Cheyenne and Nick and April
Feruli, care of NAS Investment Group LLC
for property located at 803 West 16th
Street, 1510 Reed Avenue, 1508 Reed
Avenue, and 1506 Reed Avenue for
Greenway and compliance use.
All right, we have an opportunity here
to buy a piece of property we've been
coveting for a very long time because it
is a key piece of the greenway and the
ability for the greenway to move east
and west on along 15th Street, but it's
also really important because it's also
the connector to the Reed Avenue for a
future greenway. Does anybody in the
audience want to speak to that
connection? Jennifer, I see your arms
getting tired over there.
>> I'm gonna get a sign, Mr. Miller, you
can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller, on the purchase.
>> Uh, sorry, Jennifer. Um, uh, Mayor, can
you guys hear me? I'm sorry.
>> We can hear you, sir.
>> Mayor Collins and council, for the
record, Charles Miller, I'm speaking to
the technical standards of this purchase
and sales agreement.
Uh, the city is purchasing this property
for greenway and compliance use. It is a
profound irony to hear the word
compliance used tonight considering the
administration's earlier admissions. Uh
we have a DDA that admits to a lack of
focus on maintaining its own fiscal
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller, you're out of order.
>> I I apologize. Uh if if the city is
purchasing this property for compliance,
I have to ask whose standard of
compliance are we using?
>> Mr. That's the compliance division of
our city that uh takes care of two or
three different um uh different
>> uh subjects. They do the nuisance
abatement. They have animal control.
They have uh uh a significant impact in
in what we do as a city. This will
become a warehouse for the compliance
department.
Um uh I I appreciate the clarification
um that the city defines compliance as
nuisance nuisance abatement and weed
control. However, as a technical
auditor, I'm speaking to a higher tier
of compliance, statutory and data
compliance while the city is focused on
abating nuisances on this property.
>> Point of order. Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Miller, again, I have to agree with
my city council is calling a point of
order. We're talking about the purchase
of a building. Can you please get to
that
subject?
>> Um,
yeah.
Uh,
sorry you guys kind of keep throwing me
off here a little bit. Um,
>> I know chat, you will catch up here in a
second.
>> Well, maybe that's something that you
guys ought to consider using. Um if the
expan uh okay if the city is expanding
its physical footprint for a department
tasked with compliance that standard of
accuracy must begin at the top. We
cannot com uh claim compliance on Reed
Avenue property while the city's own
records uh
>> I'm going to call
>> discuss tonight remain in a state of
technical non-compliance.
>> Mr. Miller, again
I just I got nine people yelling point
of order at me. Mr. Miller, you're not
following our procedures. What we're
talking about is the purchase of a
building. If you can talk about that and
not bring all this other stuff in, we'd
love to hear your comments.
>> Um I I uh I just hope that you guys uh
vote this one down. Thank you.
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Alan Sheldon, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
Welcome again, Mr. Sheldon.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Uh Alan Sheldon
2. I only just really had a question. I
see that it says the appraised value of
the property was 650 and it's already
been agreed to. So that probably it's a
little retroactive. But did you guys uh
you know fight for a lower price or was
there any negotiations or was it pretty
much you looked at the appraised value,
you've wanted the property as you
mentioned and you were just like yeah
let's make a deal.
>> Mr. Mr. Sheldon, we actually hired an
appraiser ourselves and asked them to
look at this property and do that. We
also did an environmental on the
property to make sure that there was
nothing that we weren't aware of uh
before we agreed to make that purchase.
>> Okay, cool. Thank you so much.
>> Appreciate you, sir. Welcome again.
>> Jim Cheryl, w one. Being in Ward One,
I'd highly support this. Uh Mayor, if
you could go ahead and uh approve this,
it' be a good idea. um through you mayor
to Dr. Emmens you're the reason why he's
not here he might be a chat GPT so but I
highly recommend that we go and support
that being a ward one to connect the
whole greenway
>> thanks Jim
anybody else in the audience
>> all right hearing none Mr. ESel on the
purchase agreement
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve in the
amount not to exceed $650,000.
And I so move
>> second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. All right.
Comments from members of the governing
body. Mr. Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through
you. I know my colleway
aspect, but I think the compliance
aspects also important too. So, I just
want to ask Mr. Mayor, I know I asked
Mr. Found the finance committee to
explain the public the importance of
this for his department. Uh, can you
call him up and ask him to explain it to
the public? Again,
>> Mr. Fountain, we haven't seen you for a
while, sir.
>> Could you share with what you shared at
the committee meeting about why this is
important to your department?
>> I'd be happy to, Mr. Mayor, and I
apologize. Took me so long to get down
here, my leg was asleep. So, bear with
me for a second. Uh, for us, this is a
great opportunity to finally be able to
put all of our product in one location.
We operate out of a utility trailer.
Then we borrow space from other folks
throughout the city. My partners, other
co-workers, directors allow us to store
stuff in their facilities. So, anytime
you have a large cleanup, it'll it'll
depend. If it's a board up, you got to
empty all of the lawnmowers and all of
the weed eaters and everything out of
the trailer to load in the the boards
and the saws and everything else to go
and board up the property. And if you're
not boarding up property, you got to
take that stuff out so you can put in
the other stuff. We also do graffiti
removal. So, we have um sprayers and
generators and air compressors and all
that stuff. So, you have to unload all
that. It's a constant shuffle, if you
will. And then you'll spend half your
day going and getting stuff to go to a
site to then go back and take it out to
get ready to go to a different site on
the next day. We do try to really triage
most of our work that we do throughout
the city, but for us, it would be a
really nice opportunity to have a place
to store all of our products, to store
our paint. So, we spent a lot of money
on paint to uh for graffiti removal.
That's not cheap. Um and then we have to
beg for a place to stick it in the
winter. Um at one point in time, we had
a lawn mower in our office. So, that's
not really conducive to what we do here
at the city building, but we have one.
So, we'd appreciate your support this
evening and I hope the community
understands how much we appreciate it as
well.
>> So, what I'm hearing, Eric, is this is
an efficiency thing for you guys to have
everything in one spot.
>> It's an efficiency thing and it's
actually an inventory control mechanism
there. It's hard to know, you know, just
taking
hope that everything's there when you go
back to get it the next time.
>> Appreciate you, sir.
>> Thank you guys.
>> Um, Mr. Lebornne,
>> thank you, Mr. Mayor. As this discussion
has pointed out, this is an opportunity
for two really major efforts here.
connecting up out of the out of the uh
pump house area and connecting the
existing path the dead ends there and
bringing it up to Lincoln Way uh is a
very important effort because it's going
to connect the greenway eventually to
downtown with a three-way connection
that I'm sure is going to be well used
and appreciated. So, I speak very much
in favor of this and I I would point out
that uh I really appreciate how quickly
uh and how thoroughly uh folks moved on
this so that we took advantage of it
when we could. Thank you.
We didn't want to miss this opportunity.
We've been looking at this one for a
very long time. Anybody else in the
governing body?
All right. Hearing none, all those in
favor of the purchase, please signify by
saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed. The purchase and sale
agreement is approved.
>> Next item is number 29D, grant agreement
between the city of Cheyenne and the US
Department of Transportation, Federal
Transit Administration for a section
5339B competitive and section 5339
formula grant for the Cheyenne Transit
Facility renovation at 1800 Westland
Road.
>> All right. All right. Is there anybody
in the audience wants to speak to this
grant to allow us to build out our new
transit facility on Westland Road?
Hearing none, Mr. Escoel.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve in the
amount of $4,143,600.
And I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody.
Comments from the governing body. Mr.
Lebornne.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh again, this is
not a routine item and that's the reason
that I asked for it to be called off the
consent agenda. This is long planned and
very important that we bring together
those elements of our transit system.
And I I really I know it's going to take
a while, but it's going to be a great
day when those users of our transit
system no longer have to use a porta
potty and they have a decent building
for them to use. And I know it's been a
long long haul. So, I certainly uh
commend the current administration of
our transit program for putting this
together and making it happen because
its long-term benefit uh is going to be
meaningful. Thank you.
Anybody else hearing? None. All those in
favor of the grant, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed, the grant is
approved.
Next item is number 30 C on page six.
Modification to bid number E-4-25
for three fire apparatus for the city of
Cheyenne, Cheyenne Fire Rescue
Department.
>> All right, we have an opportunity here
to get a firet truck early and save some
money in the process. Um, we have three
firet trucks on order. Uh it was a
four-year wait, but we uh found an
opportunity to get a truck uh that would
come earlier and that will help with one
of our apparatus that uh is probably
ready to go into reserve status. And uh
so this would allow us to modify that uh
agreement and move one of those trucks
forward till this fall. And so we'll go
out to the audience if anybody has any
uh comments or questions about this
purchase of a fire apparatus.
All right, hearing none, Mr. Escoel.
Mr. Mayor, this item was reviewed under
other items for the agenda at the April
21st, 2026 finance committee meeting.
Therefore, provisions of title two of
the city code have been met. Mr. Mayor,
the recommendation of the finance
committee is to approve with the savings
of $44,035
on an original bid and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Was that Mr. Crave? Second. All right.
Comments from members of the governing
body.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Mr. Escal, did you have a comment, sir?
>> Ken, he's talking to you.
>> Oh, Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, Mayor Collins through you. In
looking at um this document as it's
listed on the agenda, it um says that
the funding mechanism will be the
general fund reserves and the 2027
through 2030 uh spot tax or specific
purpose option tax fund. Um, and I when
I'm looking at the added item that was
approved as of April 21st, um, and that
we've been given, it doesn't talk about
the I don't see anywhere in here where
it talks, it talks about be funded
through the spot tax, but that tax
hasn't been voted on as of yet. Um, so
are we perhaps um putting our eggs in a
basket that doesn't exist that maybe we
need to um plan to take this from
general fund reserves and then if that
becomes a option? Um it talks about
three apparatuses to be fund u through
the future um ballot item. But if that
doesn't pass,
then I I'm just wondering if the wording
on that needs to be diffed differently.
>> Dr. Al, I appreciate your comment if
you'll remember back. It's probably a
year ago or so. We and maybe it says on
there the date that we did it. Um the
lead time on fire trucks is was about
four years. And so we placed the the
purchase order for these uh with the
idea that we'd put them on the six penny
sales tax and they would come much
later. Um, and if it didn't pass, then
you know, we'd still need the fire
trucks. We'd figure out a way to pay for
it through our reserves or something
else. Um, and so to answer your
question, yes. Um, our goal and our hope
would be that this specific purpose tax
will pass in August. That sometime after
that, this this fire engine will come in
and we can pay for that truck through
that uh that that tax facility. If that
doesn't pass, uh, we still need the fire
trucks. And then we'll have to talk
about as a governing body how we're
going to go ahead and afford those. But
uh I think the I don't know if this
assumption but the the calculus we made
was that uh we're going to have to buy
them regardless. And so um that's how we
move forward. Was it a year or two ago
that we we placed this order? I don't
remember exactly when it was but it was
a while ago, two years ago we placed
these orders knowing that they're still
a couple years away.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
Any otherbody? Any
I'm getting punchy. Anyone else on the
governing body
hearing? None. All those in favor of the
purchase, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The uh the bid is
approved.
>> Next item is 32A on page eight.
Appointment of Jason Powell, Brian
Fenomore, and Paul Pomeroy to the Fire
Code Board of Appeals. Justin Trip to
the Planning Commission. Cindy Oralana
to the Housing and Community Development
Advisory Council. and Josephine Carlson
to the Historic Preservation Board.
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second,
>> moved by Dr. Aldre and seconded by Mr.
White. Um the mayor doesn't get to vote
on his uh appointments, but I will run
the the vote. All those in favor of the
appointments, please signify by saying I
>> I.
>> Those opposed, the appointments are
approved and we thank them for being
willing to serve.
>> Voucher report. Is there anybody in the
audience or online or on the governing
body that would like to speak to the
vouchers?
>> Hearing none. Next item, please.
>> Revenue report.
>> Same thing. Revenue audience or on the
governing body.
Hearing none. Next item, please.
Announcement of a public hearing to be
held May 11th, 2026 at 6:00 p.m. in city
council chambers, 21101 O'Neal Avenue,
Cheyenne, Wyoming, and via electronic
conference meeting for micro brewery
permit application filed with the city
clerk's office for Joerger Hun Brewing
LLC doing business as Jagger Hun Brewing
3521 East Lincolnway, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
Other business.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience that would like to speak to us
under other business? Jim, I knew you
were sitting there for a reason.
Well, I'm glad you stuck through with
us. Thank you, sir.
>> Jim Churro, award one. Uh, thank you,
mayor. Just want to commend you guys for
putting up with all that. I remember
when I was on the HOA board um with
Robert's rule of order. Um, usually
after the second time, you got them. The
first time their point of order, the
second time there's an appeal, and then
that's it. It just it drags it on. I
know everybody's got a voice. Everybody
should have a voice on it, but again,
Dr.
I think it's a chat GPT that you're
talking to at times up there. Um, I
already spoke with Mr. Cobb. He's
working with me on some of the issues
that I had last time when I was up here.
I try to attend all the meetings. I just
want to kind of warn about expansion.
Um, my mom lives out in Chandler. They
just turned down one of those uh data
centers out there. I don't know if you
guys remember way back when um Sim City
first came out. It's a little video game
that you played on your computer and you
expanded your city. You expanded your
city and that. But as you're expanding
it, you had to use monies and stuff to
repair roads and that like stuff was
crumbling on there and that. We've
already spoken about it downtown. Been
I've been going to Frontier Day since
like 2010. I bought property out
Medicine Bow. Are they still here? No,
they're not here. They want a data
center. I'll sell them my property out
there off of Marshall Road. Medicine Bow
could use the uh the population in that.
But just I guess kind of be forewarned
about expanding too much because there's
a lot of infrastructure. I've talked to
Mr. Cobb. I've spent probably
500 pound bags of concrete fixing curbs
for my neighbors on 20th on Huger on
19th and that and it's just like
downtown is we got frontier days coming
up. He already explained to me that's
why dot but right around the plaza area
for five years some of the curbs and and
the sidewalks areas you're crossing to
go over to the Hardies and that has just
been deteriorating. But just watch the
growth. I know we need the growth. I
move here from Florida. I don't want it
to be Florida. I don't want it to be for
Collins. You know, we can we can do
other things. I pray to God that that
the railroad comes to fruition and and
gets off their butt and and everything
comes together. If not, let's use the 9
million. And when I say 9 million, you
got the five million out of reserves and
then another four for infrastructure and
that. Let's do a ballpark. If they if
you build it, they will come. And if you
ever seen the Savannah banana uh
bananas, that would be awesome to host
that in Cheyenne. So, thanks for your
time. Appreciate it. Thanks for sitting
through with us,
>> Jennifer.
>> Alan Sheldon, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Yeah, thank you. Uh, Alan Sheldon Word
two. Um, I actually ditto what gentleman
just ahead of me said. Um, I also saw
that article from Chandler, actually
have ties to Chandler, so I was quite
impressed by their decision to um,
decline that. Um, but I actually would
like to speak about the oversized
vehicle ordinance which was pushed to
the finance committee. Um, I know that
that'll be pushed to the finance
committee, so I'll try to join that
meeting. But I just want to speak to it
um just kind of to express my
disappointment that that's coming up. It
looks like based on the amendment I'm
seeing here that it it undoes a lot of
the uh compromise that people worked
really hard to get uh at the end of
2024. Um, and so, um, you know, I guess
we'll be speaking about this, um, as
these things come forward. Uh, but thank
you for the opportunity to speak
tonight.
>> Thanks, Alan.
>> Anybody else? Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller,
>> um, can you hear me?
>> We can.
Okay.
Mr. Miller.
>> Sorry. Uh, okay. Um, Mayor Collins,
Council, for the record, Charles Miller,
I'm speaking to the administrative and
technical standards established in
tonight's record. Um, the fiscal uh to
tonight, this council heard a staggering
admission from the Downtown Development
Authority that a 2023 COVID program
remains on the books in 2026 because of
a lack of focus and turnover.
Um, as a technician, I'm informing you
that turnover is a human reality, but it
is not a technical excuse. If your if
your system of record is so fragile that
it collapses when a when a staff member
leaves, you do not have a functional
administration.
You have a legacy of errors. We are
appointing new board members tonight
into this exact environment of
administrative amnesia.
Um,
okay. Then uh we then moved to the Cox
Ranch annexation where it was admitted
on the record that the city is utilizing
approximate maps which I have termed
false maps because the actual surve Mr.
Miller that does not happen point of
order for for other business. Is that
correct?
>> No, I'm I'm just saying what you're
saying is not factually correct and my
council is saying they don't want to
hear that.
>> But this is open forum here. Can can I
continue? It's it's it's other business.
>> I mean I I think it's okay. But to but
to say that it's uh
>> I believe you guys are taking my time
now
>> just
>> uh you're making Okay. So I'll just
>> Mr. Miller we did we've never admitted
on this record that we have faulty
boundaries for the Cox Ranch annexation.
>> Never possible Mr. Mayor to respond
after I speak.
>> No I I want to correct the record so
that when people hear what you're saying
they realize what you're saying is
incorrect sir.
>> Okay. Would it be possible for you to to
do that after my time is up?
>> It would be possible, but probably not
going to happen.
>> Oh, okay. Well, then I'll quickly read
the rest of what I got. Um, okay. You're
making permanent legal findings under
WS151402
based on data that does not yet exist.
To the council members who suggested
this scrutiny is nuisance or AI
generated. Uh I if a human auditor can
identify statutory non-compliance in
your own planning documents, the issue
isn't the messenger, it's the technical
fraud embedded in the maps. Uh finally,
we addressed the 1600 16,000 home water
load deficit. The administration's
response was not a hydraological data
set, but a domestic swimming pool
analogy. You cannot manage a high plains
aquifer with analogies. Tonight, the
city also purchased a warehouse for
compliance while defining that word as
mowing weeds. I urge the council to use
the upcoming retreat not for macro
goals, but for a technical reset. You're
operating on lowfidelity data,
approximate maps, and ghost budgets.
Sarcasm will not fill the water tanks,
and Robert's rules will not fix a broken
survey. Telemetry is truth. Thank you. I
also wanted to indicate that um possibly
um uh you guys should try to figure out
what's able to be discussed and and
what's not during different items. uh
because and then then share that
information amongst the the different
heads of different boards that you guys
have that way that there's um you know
to not mis uh you know confusion there.
Uh thank you
>> open invite to come visit us.
>> Mr. Miller again I'm going to challenge
you sir. Um you said that we're using
how many gallons of water? 16 million
gallons or what was that number you
quoted?
>> Uh 16,000 home loads. And what does that
come to in gallons?
>> Let's see here.
>> Type it in.
>> Uh what where is this at? Uh it's it's 3
to 400 gallons per day for a single
family home. Uh 16,000 homes times 350
gallons a day equals 5.6 million gallons
per day. Um, and that's approximately
two billion gallons a year, but it's
probably only um on a a day that they
have to uh revert to that system if it's
too hot.
>> And Mr. Miller, when you look at that,
what kind what kind of a cooling system
is that? Is that an evaporative cooling
system?
>> What is what is what does it say it is?
>> Um, well, I I I uh I urge you to look at
the failover systems that they that they
have in place when when they're closed
loop systems. uh are not uh functioning.
Um but I I appreciate uh the the time
and uh I hope you guys have a great rest
of your night.
>> All right. Thank you, Mr. Miller. Does
anybody in the governing body want to
speak under other business?
>> Mr. Mayor, Dr. Renie,
>> Dr. Renie,
>> just through you to Mr. Miller. He
apparently I want to reaffirm what you
and Mr. White on our from our planning
office said, our maps are accurate. Ms.
Woodhouse pointed out that if they were
going to carve out the mausoleum and the
easement for the mausoleum from the
property, the Cox property, then surveys
would have to be done to have the
correct definitions and description.
That was her that was her comment about
needing a new survey, which is entirely
accurate. our maps are correct, but if
they want to carve out for the
mausoleum, it has to be surveyed once
again. And I unfortunately, Mr. Miller
apparently missed that point.
>> Thank you, Dr. Rainey. Dr. Alders.
>> No,
>> I'm just Okay,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor, for very
quickly. Um, just two points. Um, we're
having a council and coffee uh this
Saturday from 9 to 11 at the Pioneer uh
center on Talbot Courts. Thank to
Director Sanchez for making those
arrangements. I invite anybody to come
whether they're in Ward One or not. Um
we're going to uh answer questions about
data centers uh and anything else
anybody like to talk to. Second of all,
um uh Dr. Aldridge and I went to the
ribbon cutting for the organ alliance,
organ donor alliance, and um and they
gave me this lovely tie. Um and um for
anybody who worries about that, it's not
very expensive, but um I was honored to
get it. And um organ donation is a huge
and important issue. It was held at the
DMV offices on Etapair.
um and um we um we were delighted to
attend and and uh Dr. Aldridge uh made
some um terrific remarks. So, thank you,
>> Mr. Secret.
>> Very briefly, Mr. Mayor. Last uh
Thursday, I had an opportunity to fill
in for you actually at the Arbor Day
celebration and we had the Fairview
third and fourth graders there. Uh it
was fabulous. It was kind of windy, but
it was a fabulous event. Um, the youth
got to hear all about Arbor Day and then
they actually, uh, planted four trees.
So, uh, very fun event. Sorry you missed
it, but glad I got to go.
>> I I was very disappointed not to be
there. It's one of my favorite events
all year long. And so, thank you for
filling in. Uh, if there's nothing else
for the agenda, we are adjourned.
>> Oh, Jeff, I'm so sorry, sir.
>> That's okay. just just one item and I
was going to announce the council and
coffee this weekend, but um there are a
couple of events next week that I wanted
to just bring to the attention of folks.
Next uh Thursday, May 7th is a youth
event and the on Friday, May 8th is the
uh 21st anniversary of the Cheyenne Day
of Giving. And um this event uh was
founded by Greta Marorrow, a former
English teacher at Cheyenne Central when
uh
>> back in when Robin and I were students
there. We won't go back to how far how
long ago that was, but uh Miss Marorrow
uh passed away
in the last six months. And so uh this
year's event will be in honor of her. Uh
they will be taking things such as non-p
perishable foods, hygiene items,
eyeglasses and hearing aids, craft
items, prescription meds, uh used
furniture, kitchen wear, and medical
equipment and supplies. And having
volunteered at this event, oh, there'll
also be an opportunity to donate blood.
Uh all one has to do is pull up at the
uh Kowanas Community House between the
hours of 8 and 4 and they will help you
unload any items you may have to donate.
>> But they won't take your blood and
drive-thru, will they?
>> They won't take your blood and
drive-thru. That that probably would
cause a traffic uh delay uh there and
and clog up things. But you can go
inside to the community house and donate
blood. Uh you do not have to have an
appointment.
>> Mr. White. Greta's uh Greta's legacy is
incredible how one person or really
small group of people can can do so
much. I was at the uh organizing event
and it also speaks really highly to
Greta because with she's still there,
but there's an amazing group that has
taken on her work and we'll make sure
that it goes on into the future. Uh and
I think the thing that's really cool for
me is I go and load things up inside the
community house. You drop those things
off that day, they're put in a box, and
that night they're at that agency. So,
they're at Boys and Girls Club, they're
at needs, they're they're at all of
those agencies that evening. Um, it's it
it's something to beheld when you get to
watch and see how it is. So, uh, big
thanks to Greta. Her memory and her
legacy is, uh, it's pretty incredible.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> uh, Mayor Collins, I just wanted to
remind everyone that, uh, we have some
amazing volunteers in our community. uh
youth alternatives will have their
volunteer appreciation banquet on Friday
evening and um recognizing all of those
individuals that make a difference for
the youth in our community. So hope to
see everybody there
>> and the main speaker will be Dr.
Aldridge.
>> I saw that Mr. Mayor just just one
further point. Yes, congratulations uh
Dr. Aldridge. Um and um just on behalf
of the Rotarians uh on uh the council
which is uh Councilman Lebornne, uh Dr.
Aldridge and myself um we'll be honored
to and Oh, that's right. And Kathy and
Council Councilwoman Emmens um we're
going to be honored to have the mayor um
speak at our noon Rotary meeting this
Wednesday and give us the state of the
city.
>> Looking forward to it. Thanks for the
invitation.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks everyone. Good night.